Okay. Um, good morning. So, the live
stream is on. So, um, yesterday you had
a chance to ask questions about the
previous class and that went very well.
So, I want to thank you for asking a
great question. you went back, you
reviewed
um what we learned and you matched our
ideas with the text and you recognized
that there's a sentence, right, which is
you shoot the arrow, you shoot the
arrow, it lands first, then it uh flies,
then it is released from the bow, right?
That's a great question. And then Carol
had a great response and because she's
actually studying this text and um so
this is exactly the sort of interaction
that I want in the seminar where you
guys are really analyzing the text
critically and this is forcing us to
think deeper about the meaning of the
text. Okay. And this is exactly, you
know, what Yale tries to achieve in its
seminars back in New Haven. So, let's
begin with questions from yesterday. You
had a chance to go back and review the
text. Again, it's really important that
you guys spend time rereading the text
to make sure you understand what's going
on. Okay. So, any questions from
yesterday that you had? Yes.
you need to press on to for other people
to hear.
>> So like in candle 6 uh there is like
this narrative of Rome's history and
something that really confused me is
actually a historical reference. So
okay so it said starting when Could you
give us a line please?
>> Where do where do you see the line?
on the on the
>> Oh,
>> her version doesn't have the
let's try to use one version. Okay. Um,
as you can see, this is the minimum
version of the Colombia website. Okay,
let's let's just use that guys so that
we are aligned. Uh,
>> the problem is I put metal bomb on both
sides while only the Italian version is
numbered. Only the Italian version is
numbered.
Yeah, they're on the same line.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I know. So like uh I was
talking about line 36 when palace died
that it might gain a kingdom. So
according to my understanding palace,
the story of palace and Aphina is a very
Greek story and it doesn't have like
much re relevance to the Roman Empire.
Uh it's a very personal Athena story.
So, what does this have to do with the
history?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Um, does
anyone know the answer? It's actually a
very hard question. So, I want to thank
you for pointing this out. So, Palace
and Athena were twins, right? And um,
Athena had to kill Palace in order to
live.
The [clears throat] story of the
founding of Rome is that Ramlas and
Remis were twins
and they grew up together and they
um rose up together and they loved each
other and then um after they defeated
like an evil uncle, they were assigned a
plot of land which became modern day
Rome. The two go to Rome and they decide
we can't rule Rome as twins. One of us
has to be the king, the other has to go
away. And so there this competition,
this competition leads to a war where
Ramlas kills Remis. Okay. [snorts] And
this is interesting because this is
actually a very
um
uh common archetype in something called
protoindo-uropean
mythology. Okay, protoindo-uropean
mythology some of you may know is the
basis for European culture. Okay. So, um
the arch ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar
ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar
archaeologists believe that the
protoindo Europeans uh lived in the
steps of modern day Ukraine. They spread
around the world to Europe to India to
Iran
and they really conquered most of the
world and they did so with a certain
mythology of conquest. Okay. And at the
very basis of this mythology is that um
you must kill the person you love. You
must kill your twin in order to climb to
power. And this is what it it refers to.
All right. So what Donnie is doing what
what he does throughout the divine
comedy which is very confusing for
people is that he tends to combine myths
together. Okay. So you have the myth of
palace and Athena. What he's saying is
that that refers to
the myth of Ramos and Remis, right?
Because we all know because in this
context, okay, this is the 14th century.
Obviously, you're you have to be very
well educated to read Dante. So,
everyone knows the mythology of Ramas
and Remis. And then what uh Dante said
does in this one line is it also reminds
us of the legend of palace and Athena.
Okay, does that make sense?
>> Um a follow-up question because
according to my understanding and
according to Wikipedia which is not a
credible source but is valuable for
basic understanding uh palace and Aphina
were not in direct opposition like they
were not fighting over a territory.
Athena lock palace and accidentally
killed her. So, uh while the theme of
killing a twin is the same, I don't see
how this has to do with a territorial
dispute.
>> Okay. Um so, um again, the idea is that
um
you must kill someone you love in order
to fully become yourself.
Okay. So, so that's what poetry is.
Poetry presents
um two ideas that may not be
interrelated and it forces you to use
your imagination in order to relate the
two things. You're absolutely right.
Like Palace and Athena, Ramis and Remis,
I didn't see the connection. And what
Donnie is doing is by putting put them
together in a with um with the grammar,
it forces you to see the connection.
Okay. What is a simile? A simile is an
unseen connection, right? The sky is a
snail. Okay.
All right. The sky and snail, they have
nothing to do with each other, but
because I put these two together, it
activates excites your imagination to
see the connection. Okay. That's what
poetry is. Does Does that make sense?
>> Okay. All right.
>> Yes. Thank you, Carol. Yes.
Um, thank you so much for um, the
questions. Um, I want to preface today,
it's our third day, and say that um,
I've been really grateful for the open
and candid dialogues and questionings
we've had because this may not be
happening elsewhere in the world. Um,
that's one. So, kudos to all of you.
Second, um I was um very happy to hear
from one of you this morning who said I
love the music because um I played some
music before class started this morning
and it was actually Jack Johnson whom
someone else said um was from his
college days. Um, the reason I played
some music, um, is because, um, I want
to read a really short portion of his
lyrics to you and kind of, um, give you
a glimpse of how I think, um, it might
be helpful to be approaching um, Dante
and poetry and beautiful works of art
um, in general. So, this is um, from 20
years ago, upside down, Jack Johnson.
Who's to say what's impossible? Well,
they forgot this world keeps spinning.
And with each new day, I can feel a
change in everything. And as the surface
breaks, reflections fade, and in some
ways, they remain the same. And as my
mind begins to spread its wings, there's
no stopping curiosity.
So, um,
I hope to be hearing from more and more
of you. um hear that you're curious,
hear that you're adding to the
conversation. Um you know, even even
despite thinking that you you may
disagree amongst yourself. Um but that's
part of um the leap of faith that John
talked about yesterday. So thank you.
>> Well, thank you, Carol. Um absolutely.
Um, and as you can see, what's happening
is that across time, across space,
different artists, whether they're
poets, they're musicians, they're trying
to convey the same message. So, you have
to think it might be from the same
source, right? Uh, and that's what Dante
is trying to explain in Divine Comedy.
There is a common source and from this
common source, uh, we can generate our
creativity. Okay. Any other questions
from last class before I begin? Yes.
Thank you.
So, I don't have a question related to
like the wording, but I I was just
rereading this and looking at the art in
like the digital Dante, and something
striking about Beatatrice is that she
actually looks kind of masculine. So,
I've been to like those um art museums
where they have like medieval galleries
and I think that the women did look
different. So, they had like veils and
they were wearing dresses. But Beatatric
here, at least on the digital Dante
website, doesn't really look like a
girl. So, like is this be is was this
like purposeful in a way or something?
>> Um
what is Okay. Um I don't know enough
about Renaissance art to comment. Okay.
But
um let's imagine what's happening. Okay.
So last cl la yesterday we discussed how
Dante is able to conceive the divine
comedy. Okay. And so Donnie is starting
off with a framework that enables him to
construct the divine comedy. Okay. So
think of this as the blueprint or the
scaffolding that allows you to slowly
visualize the entire building.
This framework must be
the dialogue between Dante and
Beatatrice. Okay, does that make sense?
Okay, so even from an early age,
he knows Beatatrice, he falls in love
with Beatatrice. Um they don't really
but they really don't know that each
other. And so what happens is that he
imagines Beatatrice as his basically
imaginary best friend or and in the
future as um his lover. Okay. Now the
problem with this is you don't know
enough about Beatatrice in order to make
Beatric a fully fleshed out character.
So what happens is Beatatrice becomes
your alter ego. Okay? It becomes like a
yin-yang dynamic,
right? Where you are implanting your
feminine aspects onto Beatrice.
And so, in other words, Beatrice doesn't
really exist as a real person. Beatrice
is just
Dante's twin basically.
>> So, like a reflection of Dante that's
like higher and more divine.
Okay, it's actually much more
complicated than that, which is that if
you study this um occult esoterism, this
mysticism, what they believe is that we
are a reflection of God. And God is
always a dual nature, both a masculine
and a feminine. Okay? So, within us,
there's always a masculine and a
feminine. So, what Donnie has done is
basically is split himself into two.
He's Daunty the masculine and um Beatric
the feminine. Okay. So um again I don't
know but what I think if I'm a painter,
I'm an artist and I recognize this, what
I'm trying to do is show that Beatrice
is just an alter ego of Dante. Okay,
does that make sense?
>> Yeah.
>> And again, I'm just speculating. Okay,
I'm just using my imagination as to what
what has happened because because I'm
not the artist, okay? I I don't know
what's going on, but this is really
important for you guys to appreciate
that the process process of creativity,
the process of um imagination requires
you to recognize your dual self, split
yourself off and have a dialogue within
yourself that becomes the basis for the
creation of whatever art you create,
whether it's a painting or a poem or
even a building. Okay? Okay. And this is
usually how the creative process works.
All right. Okay. Any more questions?
Got one. Um, so we we expanded our idea
of vows and I was trying to think about
um Pakarda made a vow in the nunnery to
God. I was trying to think of
brother seemed to make a vow on the
battlefield.
>> We just imagine that. Oh, we just
>> we don't know.
>> But but like a person could just say um
if this happens then I swear to God
something something and that's a vow.
>> I was wondering what other vows a person
would make.
>> Um a common person just an everyday and
so I could I could think of like
marriage vows is is a simple one.
Baptismal vows might be made for you on
your be because Anabaptists don't exist.
And so um what other vows might occur in
everyday society that you're breaking?
because you don't have to just walk
around going, I swear to God if I get an
A, I'm going to do XYZ.
>> Okay. Yeah, that's a really interesting
question. So, what I will say is that
what Donnie will say is to be fully
human, you must get into the habit of
making vows to yourself. Okay? Because
that ultimately is what motivates you,
what drives you to high to a higher
good,
right? Making a vow means being able to
have hope in the future and loving
yourself, having faith in the universe.
Okay, so these are three ideas that
we'll talk a lot about for the next two
days. Hope, love, and faith. So making a
vow is an expression of hope, love, and
faith. So you should be doing this every
single day.
Okay. Okay. Any more questions?
Okay. All right. So, um
I want to begin class by talking about
why we're here. Okay. So, I I want to ex
I want to talk about two basic
principles.
The first principle is
what is our mission? Okay. And our
mission is to share
Dante
with
the world. Okay. So the construction of
this class, the structure of this class,
it's unique because there are three
things that make this class different
from others in the world. Okay. First of
all, I hate to say this, but it it's
free, guys. All right? And this has to
do with the generosity of Carol who's
and and I'm me as well because because
I'm teaching this for free but this is
an amazing space. Um people online
cannot see this but this is but we are
really on top of Beijing. You know this
is a panoramic panoramatic view of
Beijing. For those of you who are in
Beijing for the first time I'm sure this
is an extremely impressive view. So
first of all it's free. Okay you guys
are here. I mean like I know some of you
have have you know flown from far away
but basically it's a free class. Okay,
that's number one. Number two is
um the diversity of the students in this
class. So again people at home don't see
this but we have students from all age
groups. Okay we have adults, we have
even a ninth grader believe it or not.
Um we also have
people from different cultures from
different um countries who've come a
long way. Okay. So just the diversity of
this class it's also unique right and
the third thing is that we are live
streaming everything we do. Okay.
Nothing is rehearsed. If I say something
stupid it's going to live forever
online.
Okay. So the question then is why is a
class constructed in this way? It's
free. It's diverse and it's being
livereamed. And the reason why is that
as a group
we are trying to prove to the world that
anyone anywhere can love Dante.
Okay? Regardless of your culture,
regardless of your age, you can love
Dante. Dante speaks to you individually.
And
together we're trying to show the world
that anyone can read and love Dante and
give them the tools and the thought
processes in order to fully understand
Dante uh and set everyone on that
journey.
Um, I hope that regardless of where you
are, whether you're in Africa or South
America or even um the Arctic, who
knows? But this class will inspire you
to partake in your own journey. And this
class will give you all the tools you
need in order to fully appreciate Dante.
So, our mission here is to share Dante
with the world. Okay. It is an act of
love. It is act of faith. It is an act
of hope. And we have to remember that
that is our central mission. In order to
achieve the central mission, you
yourselves must in this room, okay, must
fully engage Dante and fully put your
heart into Dante. And to do that, you
have to remember how to truly understand
Dante. And the trick is this, okay? It
is to
learn Dante
so that you may
teach it
as an act of love.
Okay. So this is the key. If you truly
want to understand Dante, you have to
read and learn Dante.
And imagine that you're doing so so that
one day you can teach it to someone that
you truly love as an act of love.
All right? So every day after class, you
you should go home and visualize that
one day. You could have your own
classroom with your own students or you
could have your own children
or you could be talking to your mother
over the dinner table or you could be
talking to your best friend. It doesn't
matter. Okay? But imagine yourself like
Dante in heaven with Beatatric. And what
are they doing? They are debating each
other. They're learning together.
They're sharing with each other. That is
the true act of love. Okay. So I
guarantee you you put yourself in the
frame of mind that I'm here today so
that tomorrow I can share Dante with
someone I love as an act of love. You
will truly
understand Dante.
Okay. So these are the two things I want
you to keep in mind. Our mission here in
this classroom is to co-create together
a classroom so that
everyone in the world can listen in and
love Dante. We we are spreading Dante
throughout the world. That is our
central mission. Nothing else comes
before this. And second, if you're truly
to understand Dante, if you're truly to
read the Divine Comedy and understand
what's going on, you have to commit
yourself to loving someone and sharing
Dante with that person. It could be
anyone. It could be your mother. Uh it
could be your brother. It could be your
student. It doesn't matter. And but it
has to be a real person, guys. Okay?
All right.
Having said that, I want to explain why
it's important to share Dante with the
world. Okay. All right. So, let's go to
the year 1300. In the year 1300,
there are many places in the world,
okay? In the Middle East, there's
something called the Islamic Golden Age,
okay? Islam, Islamic Golden Age.
In China and in Asia there is the Pax
Mongalika.
The Mongols are in charge.
Um in Central America you have the
Mayans. Okay.
And in Europe you have uh medieval
Europe
you guys can't appreciate this but in
the year 1300 medieval Europe was
essentially a hole. Okay? It was
the worst place in the world to be.
Excuse me.
Basically the dark ages. Yes.
>> Um I find that a very reductionist view
to be honest. Like uh a lot of people
say bad things about the middle ages. I
agree middle ages bad place to be
compared to now compared to the
Renaissance. But we have to admit that
the middle ages were were the foundation
for what became the Renaissance. And the
renaissance did not change things much
for the average person. It changed
things a lot for the intellectuals and
for the high class people. I think
that's important to keep in mind.
>> Okay. So, so I'm trying to make a point
here. Okay. The point is that in your
1300, if you were Mayan and you visited
Europe, if you were living in Baghdad,
you visited Europe. If you were living
in China, you visit Europe, you would
think this place is a hole. Okay?
You would think this place is hopeless.
These people are barbarians. All they do
is kill each other. There is censorship.
There is there is no learning. It's all
in anti-arning, anti-intellectual.
But at the same time, 20 years in the
future, there is there's not there's a
renaissance which then leads to the
second revolution, the enlightenment,
the age of conquest where Europe will
span out and conquer everyone. Okay. All
right. So the question is how did this
happen? Why is it in the year 1300, you
go there and you think these people are
completely hopeless, right? It's like
basically like us, I hate to say this,
but it's like basically us going to the
mi to the Middle East right now and
saying, "Oh my god, these pl this place
is hopeless. They're all killing each
other. There's endless war. They can't
agree on anything. There are they are in
anti-arning, anti-intellectual. This
place is completely hopeless."
How was it possible that 20 years later
you would have the renaissance, you have
this emergence of Europe? And my answer
is Dante. Okay, it is because of what
Dante did because of what? Because of
the divine comedy that Europe would then
go on to expand itself to change itself.
And then the question then is okay how
is Dante able to fundamentally change
the character of the Europeans
and it's the divine comedy and what I
will show you is that
he places three things before all
others. Okay. He he fundamentally
reimagines what it means to be human by
placing three virtues above all else.
They of course are faith,
hope,
love. Now you think yourself, wait a
minute here, this is just the Christian
virtues, okay? The only difference is,
okay, back then you had faith, hope, and
then it was charity.
So what's the big deal here? The big
deal is how Dante will come to define
these terms. Okay, divine comedy
fundamentally is trying to show you what
these ideas really mean. So for Dante,
faith is the belief
and the understanding of the nature of
God. Right?
Faith is to understand that God is first
and foremost love and God is not this
vengeful
uh spiteful entity but this all
forgiving
all generous allloving source. Okay,
that is what the faith is. Second is the
idea of hope. The idea of hope is that
by making vows,
you can create for yourself your own
future that you imagine it to be.
Okay. So hope is fundamentally not a
passive thing where you pray to God and
hope God gives it to you but you
actively imagine yourself and then God
co-creates with you.
And love
for Dante is the unifying force of the
universe. It is what God is. It is what
connects us to each other. Okay, love is
about connection.
Now then the question then is okay if
this is what Donnie said, how is this
different from the Catholic Church or
what Paul said? Okay.
And so um what Dante
says is this.
For faith, hope and love to exist in the
world, it has to be an active act of
imagination.
Okay? Do you understand? These things
don't exist by themselves. They're not
given us to by by God. It is imagined by
us in this world. Okay? And what allows
for the imagination to take place is
poetry
which of course is divine comedy.
So imagine divine comedy as really the
big bang of western civilization. Okay.
It is what starts our journey because it
enables enables us to imagine faith,
love and hope.
All right. Um so for people at this time
in the middle ages this is a revolution.
We don't think this is a big deal now
because because we live in a world
created by Dante. But before Dante
before the big bang people imagine these
things as fundamentally about obedience.
Okay? Just obey authority. Obey the
church. Obey the priest and you'll be
good. That is what faith, love and hope
is. Okay. Now what's interesting is that
this idea that everything is based on
obedience also comes from poetry
but it is Virgil okay the iniad and this
something we'll discuss
um
later on okay next week. Okay do you
understand? So what I'm trying to tell
you is that at the fundamental core
of the universe is a spiritual war
between two poets Virgil and Dante.
Virgil through his poetry makes us
believe that through obedience we can
achieve faith, hope and love. But what
Donnie is doing with divine comedy is
arguing that no it must be for our
imagination
in which we are able to achieve faith,
love and hope. Okay. So this is the this
basically the framework for this class.
This is the grand thesis I I will
present to you as we go along. Okay.
These next few days we will study why
faith, hope and love are important and
how Dante will conceptualize this. And
then starting uh um after the break we
will go into this larger cosmic war
between Virgil and Dante to reimagine
humanity. All right. So that's a plan.
Uh yes.
>> So my first question has to do uh with
the very euroentric nature of this
so-called cosmic war. So Virgil and
Dante are both Europeans. And I think it
might be more appropriate to say that
this is a war fought on the European
thoughtscape rather than across the
entire cosmos. And the second part is
I'm a little bit confused when you're
talking about obedience. So you said
that Dante speaks against obedience, but
he speaks for the obedience of vows and
obedience to God. So how is that
different?
>> Okay. So let me ask you your second
question first. Okay. Okay. So it's
really a difference between how you
perceive your role in the world. Are you
an active participant in the world or
are you a passive participant in the
world? According to Virgil, according to
the Catholic Church, um um I should also
point out that this idea of obedience
comes from two major theologians of the
Catholic Church. There of course are
Paul and Augustine. Okay. Paul who is
the founder of Catholic Church and
Augustine who is the major theologian of
the Catholic Church who will systemize
the teachings of Paul. Okay. But they
get the but they get the ideas from
Virgil. All right. So um so
um
the um what Augustine teaches people
that is very important is that because
of the original sin because of our
disobedience from God humans are
inherently evil.
If you're inherently evil, you should
probably not do too many things. Okay?
Because all you do is create more evil
in the world. Therefore, you should just
obey. And if you obey and you avoid sin,
that is the that is the fastest path to
heaven. Okay? Does that make sense? Just
obedience. Do what the church tells you
and you will do good in the world or you
will not do evil in the world and then
you will ascend to heaven. Okay? So this
it's a very fatalistic very pessimistic
worldview.
Okay. So that's a major difference.
Yes.
>> Uh can I add to this? I actually was
rereading and and researching last night
uh City of God by Augustine and he would
say that because of the fall, let me
pull up my notes. because of the fall.
Um,
uh, Jesus was the only perfect person
because Adam was exiled from the Garden
of Eden. Adam's sin essentially damaged
human nature.
>> That's right.
>> And the damage itself was inherited by
all the descendants of Adams
>> through the mechanism of of semen.
Right. And this it's this concept of
every human has sexual desire almost as
a punishment.
And um even the people even the saints
and the and most holy people of all time
uh who denied themselves they would they
would be um what do you call celibate
they they're denying themselves sexual
desire uh Augustine calls this fake he
is not impressed with this at all and he
would say like it's a person who's like
fasting they still they're still hungry
right and it's that hunger that desire
that's the that you cannot fake it's
still there Right. Um and
so the greatest saint and the worst
criminal are all equally fallen before
God.
>> Yes. Exactly. So as so so you can
appreciate this is what's being taught
in in at this time, right? We are just
completely hopeless. We are beyond
salvation. We are just beyond
redemption. Just don't cause any
trouble, guys. Just obey and then and
then when you die, maybe God will save
you. Okay? So, it's a very pessimistic,
very fatalistic viewpoint. But when you
read a lot in comedy, it's very
optimistic.
Um, it's very hopeful. Okay. It's it's
just emits love. Okay. So, thank you so
much for for that. Okay. All right.
Great. All right. So, let me ask you the
second question, which is Urgil and
Dante are European and so therefore they
don't speak for all of humanity. Okay.
So, I'm going to get into a lot of
trouble for saying this, but I don't
perceive
poetry as culturally
uh located. Okay. I think poetry is
universal. The entire point of teaching
Dante in Beijing in the year 2026 to
mostly Chinese students from different
age groups, high school, university,
adults is to prove the universality of
Dante.
Right?
So if e if Dante is only European,
why is it that we have students from
China who are really focused on Dante,
who find inspiration in Dante? Why is it
that if culture really m matters that
much,
how are how are we able to create this
classroom?
Could could you answer that? What I'm
saying is not that they are limited to
Europe. I'm saying that they are only
representative of Europe. So it's like
it's like there are so many types of
poetry out there. And you're basically
saying that these two are the
archetypes. These two are the big bads.
These two are the big bads fighting out
against each other. I'm saying there
might be better archetypes out there.
There might be different archetypes out
there also fighting it out. And I'm
saying but like rather than just saying
there might be give me an example.
Um I'm not sure I could pronounce the
name but uh for example like in India
there are different types of poetry and
holy scripture and they're one one of
these I remember is called the aranyaka
and they're about the forest they're
about uh the primal the the primal
nature of man. So instead of talking
about uh obedience versus disobedience
maybe we can talk about civilization vs
uh primal nature of man. I'm just saying
these are different perspectives that
Virgil and Dante do not encapsulate.
>> Um, okay. So, I don't know enough about
Indian poetry to comment. Okay. But the
point I'm trying to make is this. Um, in
this classroom, we are making certain
assumptions. We are assuming the
universality of Dante.
Um meaning D can speak to everyone of
all cultures of all ages across all of
time. Okay. And you need that sort of
arrogance or
um
sense of supremacy in order to fully
appreciate Dante. Okay. So I appre I
understand yes there must be other great
works of literature out there.
Show it to me, okay? Rather than tell me
you're just being ignorant, you're just
being uh racist. Show me, okay? Take it
upon yourself to learn this stuff and
share with the world. I I would love to
be proven wrong about Dante. I think
Dant is the greatest poet in the world.
I think Dante speaks for everyone. I
think Dante is universal. I think it
doesn't matter if you are Chinese or if
you are Indian or if you are anyone okay
you will love Dante if you make the
effort to appreciate Dante and I don't
think anyone else compares to Dante I
make this arrogant statement and if you
say you are wrong then take the time as
I've taken the time to learn Dante and
show me another poet who is just as
worthy to learn as Dante
I'm not saying that you're racist. I'm
not saying any of these things. I don't
know why you arrived at the conclusion.
I am saying that it is part of our
academic responsibility to limit
ourselves as researchers to what we know
and what we do not. And you I agree with
you. You are making a very arrogant
statement. And perhaps that statement
has a place in this class. But my point
is it is part of your academic
responsibility to limit the scope of
that statement.
>> Okay? This is not an economic classroom.
Okay? This is not designed to be in the
classroom. I already said on our two
missions are right. Share Dante with the
world.
Right? Why do I share Dante with the
world? Because I think that in this time
and age, when there is war, when there
is hopelessness,
when there is conflict, I believe that
resuming Dante to this world, spreading
Dante to this world will give humanity
hope.
That's what I fundamentally believe.
That's what I think our mission is.
Okay? not just to share Dante with the
world, but to resummon Dante physically
into our world with our imagination so
that Dante can help save the world from
whatever we're doing.
Okay? So, keep in mind guys, this is the
point of why we're here to share Dante
with the world. That's a primary
mission.
Everything must follow from this
mission. If you're like, "No, I want to
learn D academically." There are tons of
daunting academic courses,
right?
Um Carol, when we introduced this course
online, did we not say this?
>> This is not a course.
>> Okay.
>> Academic program. Um there's, for
example, an open course by a Sterling
professor on Dante in translation. You
can look for many of these.
>> Okay. Do you understand? And that that's
why I have to emphasize. Okay. There's a
mission here. Let's stick to the
mission. If you do not agree the
mission, then
this course is probably not for you.
Okay? So, it's not a course, but but
this this this
setup, okay, or or this platform, okay,
is not for you. Okay. We are here to
truly learn to love Dante so that we may
share it with others.
Okay, any more questions before we
begin?
Okay, so what we're going to do now is
we're going to jump ahead. We're going
to skip around because I want to show to
you, all right, what how Dante is going
to recreate the idea of humanity. All
right. So, first thing is we're going to
go to Kend 11. 10 to 11. Okay.
Yeah.
All right. So, what's happening is that
Beatric and Dante are traveling through
the cosmos, right? And we're going to
skip skip around. Um, not because the
other kinds are not important. It's just
I don't I don't have as I mentioned uh
yesterday I don't have the full
knowledge to fully interpret the other
candles but I want to focus on candles
11 and 12 this morning. So what's
happening is that Dante will meet um two
individuals. The first indivi individual
is Thomas Aquinus who is
um
only second Augustine.
Um so so Thomas Thomas Aquinus is the
second most famous Catholic theologian
in the world and why he's important is
that he is going to try to reconcile
classical Greek philosophy
with the Christian faith. Okay. And he's
really the first to attempt this. Um
this is being done throughout the
throughout the world in Islamic golden
age. But again at this time um Europe is
extremely ignorant and isolated from the
rest of the world and Thomas Aquinus is
going to change that by bringing
Israelian thought back into Christian
theology. Okay. So that's Thomas
Aquinus. Thomas Aquinus is part of an
order called the Dominicans. Okay. The
Dominicans are essentially the Jesuits,
the pre- Jesuits. Um and these are
people who are dedicated to learning and
education and they are doing this in
order to better enforce Christian
orthodoxy throughout Europe. Okay. So
that's the Dominicans
and then uh in panel 12 we'll uh we will
meet um Bonaventure who is part of an
order called the Franciscan order. Okay.
Francian order was founded by Francis
Aissi who
who made a vow to poverty and this is
very similar to Jesus right Jesus as we
discussed yesterday he found a movement
called the poor uh and they made a vow
to poverty and so uh St. Francis also
made a vow to poverty. The problem with
both orders is they started out great.
Okay, their founders were visionary.
They really brought hope to the world. I
mean, the Catholic Church at this time
was being criticized for corruption
uh for engaging in worldly affairs. And
these two movements seemed the answer.
They were reform movements that seemed
to bring hope to Europe. But ultimately
both fail. Okay. So what Dante wants to
figure out is why is it that these two
movements which started out great the
Dominicans uh with their um selfless
pursuit of knowledge and the Franciscans
with their selfless pursuit of
spirituality.
Why did they fail? Okay, that's a
question before us. All right. So um can
we uh read Carol please?
This is counter 11. Okay.
>> Paradise KTO 11.
Oh senseless cares of mortals, how
deceiving are psyogistic reasonings that
bring your wings to flight so low to
earthly things. One studied law and one
the apherisms of the physicians. One was
set on priesthood and one through force
or fraud on rulership.
One meant to plunder, one to politique,
one labored tangled in delights of
flesh, and one was fully bent on
indolence.
>> Okay. So here Donnie is criticizing
academic studies, right? Okay. What is
his concern about academic studies
at this time?
What what does he mean?
>> Anyone? Uh yes.
>> They all have ulterior motives.
>> Good. Yes.
uh that they focus too much on the
material and not the spiritual.
>> Yeah, exactly. Okay. So, the idea is
syllogistic reasonings. Okay. Rather
than use your mind to pursue God and the
truth. Uh yes. Did you do you have a
question?
>> No. No. I I was trying to answer your
question too. So, like uh I'm reminded
of something in Crusader Kings the game.
Uh like you can have your priest uh
justify your claim to a plot of enemy
land through theology. So what he's
saying here, how I understand it is that
he's saying that uh theology is not
studied for its own sake but to amass
power.
>> Exactly. Okay. That that that's that's
what everyone agrees on. Right. This is
a problem with
theology with academics at this point in
history. Quite honestly, it's no
different today by the way. But um but
um uh he points out this is a real
problem. Okay. Can't keep my way.
>> Verse 10. While I delivered from our
servitude to all these things, was in
the height of heaven with Beatress so
gloriously welcomed. After each of those
spirits had returned to that place in
the ring where it had been, it halted
like a candle in its stand. And from
within the splendor that had spoken to
me before, I heard him as he smiled
become more radiant, more pure begin.
>> So he of course is Thomas Aquinus. All
right, who will explain
um the Franciscan order. Okay, so this
is weird because uh Thomas Aquinus is of
the of the Dominican order, but he'll
explain the glories of the Franciscan
order. Now what he will do is he will
criticize his own order and then the
next counter we'll meet another guy
Bonav who is of the Franciscan order
praise the Dominican order and then he
criticism on his own order. Okay. All
right. Uh keep on going.
>> Verse 19. Even as I grow bright within
its rays. So as I gaze at the eternal
light I can perceive your thoughts and
see their cause. You're in doubt. You
want an explanation in language that is
open and expanded, so clear that it
contends your understanding of two
points. Where I said they fatten well
and where I said no other ever rose and
here one has to make a clear
distinction.
>> Okay. So um so we we skipped ahead but
Thomas Aquinus already is having
conversation with Dante and they found
him well off obviously refers to
corruption in the um Catholic church.
Okay so he's trying to explain uh how
this happened. Okay, keep on going.
Okay, line 28. The providence that rules
the world with wisdom so fathomless that
creatures intellects intellects are
vanquished and can never probe its death
depth. So that the bride of him who with
loud cries had wed her with his blessed
blood might meet her love with more
fidelity and more assurance in herself
on her behalf commanded that there be
two princes one on this side one on that
side as her guide.
>> Okay. So this is the most these are the
two most important tursets of this
kanto. Okay. So let's try to unpack
this. Does anyone know what the bride of
Jesus is? The bride of God. Who what is
the bride of God?
>> Um well if I was a heretic I would say
Mary Magdalene.
>> No [laughter]
guys.
It's a Catholic church right? The bride
of God.
>> Yeah. Yeah. God is a heretic.
>> All right. The bride of God is a
Catholic church. Okay. So, how's how's
the Catholic Church founded? It was
founded uh through the sacrifice of
Jesus, right? So, after Jesus was
crucified, the Catholic Church came into
being in order to continue Jesus'
mission on earth. Right? So, the
Catholic Church made a vow to God that
we will be forever marry and I will
forever
promote your message in the world. Okay?
And in order to achieve this uh what
will happen is they will uh give rise to
two princes to ensure that the mission
continues despite the corruption and the
decay of the Catholic church and these
two princes are St. Fran Francis who
will found the Franciscan order who are
devoted to poverty and then Dominic who
founded the Dominican order who will who
will promote themselves uh who will
dedicate themselves to learning as well
as promoting um Catholic orthodoxy
throughout Europe. Okay. These are the
ones who are responsible to squash all
heresies. Okay. All right. So this is
the origins of the Catholic Church. Keep
on going. Verse
37. One prince was all sarafhic in his
order. The other for his wisdom had
possessed the splendor of sherubic light
on earth.
>> So the um so the sheriff and the sherb
are two orders of angels. Okay. So the
angels have taken possession of these
two individuals Francis and Dominic. And
it's the angels who will guide them in
their mission.
Okay.
>> Verse 40. I shall devote my tale to one
because in praising either prince, one
praises both. The labors of the two were
toward one goal.
>> Okay, so he's going to talk about
Francis. Okay, keep on going.
>> Verse 43. Between Topino's stream and
that which flows down from the hill the
blessed Ubaldo chose. From a high peak
there hangs a fertile slope. From there
Perugia feels both heat and cold at
Porto sole. While behind its sorrow,
Nosera and Gualdo under their hard yoke.
From this hillside where it abates its
rise, a son was born into the world.
Much like this sun when it is climbing
from the Ganges. Therefore, let him who
names this site not say Ashesi, which
would be to say too little, but orient
if he would name it rightly. That son
was not yet very distant from his rising
when he caused the earth to take some
comfort from his mighty influence. For
even as a youth he ran to war against
his father on behalf of her the lady
unto whom just as to death none
willingly unlocks the door before his
spiritual court at Cororum patre he wed
her day by day he loved her more she was
beereft of her first husband scorned
obscure for some years until that son
came she had had no suitor.
>> Okay. All right. So, let's try to figure
out what's going on. Okay. Francis
married someone.
Okay. He married this person in defiance
of his family, of his father.
Okay. Um, does anyone know the story of
Francis Aisi?
Okay. C can you can you u explain who
who he is and what he did? Uh so
basically he's a saint obviously and the
founder of the Francisian order and and
his whole thing is that he's really
poor. Really really really really poor.
Poorer than Augustinians, poorer than
Dominicans.
>> Okay. And
>> sorry, how did he become poor?
>> Uh he gave away all his riches.
>> Okay. So he's born rich. Okay. He was
born into a wealthy family and he said
to his parents, I don't want this. Okay.
I want poverty. So he rejected his
family. He rejected his legacy. He
rejected his community in order to wed
poverty. Okay. So the bride, she is
referring to poverty,
right? And who married poverty before
Francis?
Poverty has two husbands. Francis is the
second. Who would be the first?
Jesus, right? Okay. Jesus was the first
husband and then after he died, no one
wanted to marry her again. Okay. Like, I
don't want poverty. Screw this. Okay.
Francis is like, I will do it. I will
marry poverty. Okay. Does does that make
sense, guys? All right. So, the she
refers to poverty. Keep on going.
>> Verse 67.
Nor did it help her when men heard that
he who made earth tremble found her
unafraid, serene with Amiclas when he
addressed her. Nor did her constancy and
courage help when she, even when Mary
stayed below, suffered with Christ upon
the cross. But so that I not tell my
tale too darkly. You may now take
Frances and take poverty to be the
lovers meant in my recounting. Their
harmony and their glad looks, their love
and wonder, and their gentle
contemplation, served others as a source
of holy thoughts, so much so that the
venerable Bernard went barefoot first.
He hurried toward such peace, and though
he ran, he thought his pace too slow. Oh
wealth unknown. Oh good that is so
fruitful. Gideas goes barefoot and
Sylvester behind the groom the bride
delights them so. Then Francis father
master goes his way with both his lady
and his family. The lowly cord already
around their waist.
>> Okay. So he is referring to a happy
marriage right. Francis gives up
everything to marry poverty and they are
the happiest couple in the world. And
there are followers who also embrace
embrace poverty and they become a
family. Okay? And this becomes a
Franciscan order. The early Franciscan
order.
Why would you be happy marrying poverty?
This is this goes into everything that
we've been taught, right? If you want to
be happy, you must get rich. Why would
you be happy marrying poverty?
Uh yes. Like what if with without money
you can't you're like living from the
material world. So there's because
without money nothing you can buy. You
cannot get happiness from those
materials or some like physical object.
Instead you can truly find your spirits
when you don't when the material cannot
make you feel astray.
>> Yeah. Okay. So what you're saying is
that money sort of blinds you right? You
focus on money. You focus on material
world and that blinds you from a greater
truth. Okay. Good. Anyone else?
>> Oh yeah. Maybe because he want to go to
paradise, go to the heaven because if
you just do not be rich, then maybe
you'll be in heaven just like the gods
that right. So maybe.
>> Right. So Jesus said that if you are
poor, you have riches in heaven. Yes.
Okay. Blessed are the meek. Uh yes.
>> So uh he had riches first, right? And he
was giving them all away. Maybe he was
trying to do good deeds by giving alms.
>> Could could you could you elaborate on
on this? Um so like uh he has all this
money and to get rid of it to become
poor he doesn't chuck it in the river.
He gives it away to like beggars to
vagrants and even when he found his
order the Franciscan order uh there he
took in people who have no other home
and for the people who have property he
took their donations and he used it to
do good works in the local area. So it's
a way of spreading out. Are
>> you just assuming that or do you know
that?
>> Uh I read the story. Yeah.
>> Okay. So, he gave away his wealth.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. All right. But I'm saying like why
would he do that?
>> Uh yes.
>> So in the line 60 [clears throat]
uh 76 they say um their harmony and
their glad looks, their love and wonder
and their gentle consolation serve
others as a source of holy thoughts. So
probably um he's trying to show the
world that you can um also like like he
said um you can you can you can go look
for your inner um spirit and um
spiritual um enlightenment rather than
chasing money. He he as example he he
want to show the world that this is can
be a way.
>> Okay. So thank you. First of all I love
the fact that you refer to the text.
Okay this is really important guys.
We're here to learn. Dante, always refer
to the text. And second of all, you're
absolutely right in that being an
inspiration to others brings you
tremendous delight.
Right? So back to the uh uh second,
learn Dante so that you may teach it to
others as an act of love. Right? So the
reason why you do that is it makes you a
happier person. Okay? And not only does
it give you more enlightenment, it
brings greater happiness to you. So by
being a good example, by being a good
leader, he's bringing he's creating more
happiness in the world and that in him
creates more happiness. Good. Okay.
[snorts] So if
poverty can be good, why don't we do it
then?
Huh?
There's been two husbands to poverty,
Jesus and Francis. They're all saints.
Yeah. Yes.
>> Well, because we would be ostracized by
society. I mean, there's, for example,
there's also um the philosopher
Deioenist who lived in poverty like
>> the cynic. Yes. The cynic. Yes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. He lived in Athens in in a
barrel or something for for his whole
life.
>> A bathtub.
>> Or a bathtub. Yeah.
And yeah, he was also really poor and
everyone like looked down on him and
like he was ostracized and yeah,
>> but but why did he do it then? If he was
ostracized, he was humiliated. Everyone
laughed at him. Why did he do it?
>> Well, he didn't care. Like he he he felt
happy, so that's what mattered.
>> But what's the source of his happiness?
I
>> no it's like the Buddhist said you're if
you don't want then if you don't desire
then
>> you're never going to have suffering
because suffering is the point of
desire.
>> Yeah. He Yeah. Yeah. He he just didn't
want it. Yes.
>> Um so I would I would turn inwards to be
honest. I would turn inwards. I would
say this is a way for them to get closer
to God because as we mentioned before
like in Dante's own flight to paradise
uh uh
told him to shed his physical
conceptions, to shed his physical logic,
to shed his worldly veins and only when
we are pure in spirit can we reach the
heavens. Now suicide is not a thing in
Catholicism. So the closest we can get
to a state of being pure in spirit is by
getting rid of all our property and
having only this body left.
>> Okay. Right. I Yes, I understand that.
But I'm saying like why is it hard to
just do that? Why? Why do you not want
to give up your p
>> property and your wealth? Anyone? Anyone
else? Let's let's have more part
participation. Okay. Yes.
>> We don't know actually what it will be
like if we haven't experienced it
before. So what if we give everything
away in
>> Exactly. Yeah. Thank you. Okay. So we
have one which is we are we will become
socialize. Okay. Humiliation. It's
public humiliation. Okay. Everyone's
going to laugh at us. Unless you like
dio and you just don't care. Okay. But
that's pretty weird.
Uh second is uh sorry so sorry could you
repeat
>> it's that if we haven't experienced it
before we don't know what it will be
like so what if I give everything away
and then I'm actually miserable
>> so these are the two things right ego
and fear ego is you want to stand above
the people around you fear is you don't
truly know yourself you're afraid okay
so these are the two major reasons the
ego and the fear.
>> Uh yes, I
>> mean sometimes you also have like
responsibility about raising a family or
caring about like your family. So that
could be a reason like besides your ego,
you need to care for others also.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Right. If you have a
family, you can't take a vow of poverty.
You have to feed them as well. So
poverty means complete social isolation,
right? It means you can't get married.
It means you can't have kids. So it is
an act of tremendous sacrifice. Good.
Thank you. Anyone else? Yes.
>> So I think that you know when you have
like materialistic
uh goals, it kind of motivates you
sometimes. So um for example, if there's
like a test and my mom promises me like
a new iPhone 17 Pro, like I would
definitely like work harder for that.
So, I just think that for like a lot of
people, it's very hard to let go of like
their materialistic desires because then
they would feel like my life is so
devoid of meaning. And I think that
they're scared of that.
>> Yeah. So, what what you're saying is um
short-term gratification versus
long-term reward, right? Maybe if you
embrace a life of poverty, you go to
heaven and that's great, but in the
short term, you're better off just being
rich, right? So,
good. Yes. Anyone else? Yes.
>> No, sorry. Sorry. Sorry. You you Yes.
I think u [clears throat]
you know in ancient times uh in time of
um Dante uh wealth means physical
possessions
uh channels or uh or real estate and all
these carries um tremendous um
responsibilities for the person who
possess them because and this leads to
um a burdensome life. And secondly uh
and secondly uh uh just going back to
the text. I think uh [clears throat]
when uh uh the franciscan uh and the
arenas the Dominican uh they uh praise
the other and uh criticize themselves.
uh there might be a a new interpretation
which I think uh might be interesting
which uh you know if we uh uh if they
what what if these two criticize uh
themselves because
uh they do not have uh equal wealth and
equal knowledge. If uh there is the
Chinese seeing you know your your wealth
is only yours if your knowledge deser
deserve it. Uh so it means that
uh if your wealth is equal to your
knowledge maybe it's a good thing. Uh if
the wealth goes to a person who has
great knowledge and great capacity to
distribute the wealths and use the
wealths in a wise way not for them for
his family but also to for society I
think it might be a good thing.
>> Okay. So that's a very interesting
comment. Um but have we had an instance
where
a truly wise man also had tremendous
wealth? Maybe Solomon. Okay. So so so
but I mean there are examples but
historically we've we've had more cases
where you can either choose wealth or
wisdom, right? And the classic example
of course is Socrates,
a man who who was basically poor all his
life. Um, in fact, his wife made all the
money in the family. Okay, he had a
family. He had kids, but the wife had to
raise the kids because he didn't take
money for his teachings. He just went
around and taught for free. Uh, he was
engaged in in wisdom. Okay. Uh, any more
questions or comments before we move on?
>> Yeah.
Maybe because the you know uh people who
just live in ancient time they sometime
believe in God believe they are stoism
maybe but you know the world is being
regulated by the system right the system
is for rich for rich people the people
who have money it means that they have
right to talk and they have right to do
whatever they want. So maybe just
because the the social system just want
people to be rich. If you can be rich
then you'll be one of us. But if if you
do not you have your own wisdom then I'm
sorry I won't give you the right I won't
give you the money. Maybe that's the
problem.
>> Okay that's an interesting point. Okay
this is certainly true for all world
where only that matters is money. Money
moves around the world but this is not
true actually in medieval Europe. Okay.
Um medieval Europe. Yes there's
hypocrisy where the Catholic Church is
filthy rich. They own a third of all the
land in Europe. That is true. But but
what is taught what people believe is
that money is the root of all evil. So
the money doesn't matter. What matters
is salvation. What matters is going to
heaven. Okay. Okay. Yes.
>> Is it kind of gaslighting that the cath
cath Catholic church is said that they
owns like most of the land but they say
money is the root of evil but meanwhile
they have all the money and can do
whatever they want.
>> Okay. And so what would you prefer? They
own all the property and they tell
everyone, "You're nothing. I'm
everything. You guys are poor. You guys
are going to hell." Would you prefer
that?
>> Um, no.
>> Okay.
>> I would rather be deceived.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm interested about the charitable pro
concept of all of this. Like, uh, I know
this is not the modern age. Like modern
age you have to pay a lot of taxes and
the taxes go towards uh, public works
and you can donate to charity and you
have all these things going on. Um but
in the middle ages wealth was pretty
stagnant right however there are some
few charitable endeavors by believers
like there's this custom of almsgiving
by rich ladies and there's also the
Catholic church and the monasteries and
they provide sanctuary to criminals and
they provide schooling so like is that a
type of charitable outreach that would
not be possible had they not been so
organized and So rich.
>> Yeah. So charity is one of the chief
Christian virtues, right? So we say
faith, love, and hope, but back then it
was faith, hope, and charity. So if
you're a rich person, you were obligated
to share your wealth with the people
around you. Okay? Um, and guys, I it's
it's hard to imagine this, but back
then, no one really cared how rich you
were. It was not a big thing, okay?
um it was a source of a lot of
corruption but for most people they
didn't really care. Uh at the elite
politics it did matter but for most
people it did not matter. Okay, we live
in a world that is money obsessed. It is
crazy
um how we just love money. We think that
money is a source of all good in this
world for whatever reason we worship
this fake trillionaire Ellen Musk. The
guy's a fake trillionaire. Okay. All the
money he has is just made up. He doesn't
really exist and we worship him. Okay,
so anyone else from any other time in
human history comes to our day and
everyone says like you guys are the most
superstitious people in the world. Okay,
you guys worship this fake god money and
you center your entire life around it.
You guys are superstitious. You guys are
ignorant. You guys are backwards. Okay,
I guarantee you anyone who comes from
the past to today will be appalled by
the way we live our lives. All right.
Okay. So having established the fact
that is ego and fear
that prevents us from truly
understanding
God. Okay.
Um this raises the question of how then
can we
overcome the ego and the fear. Right?
That's a question.
Okay. Okay, this is a central question
if we are to save humanity or if Dante
is going to reimagine humanity. Okay,
keep this in the back of your mind. How
do you overcome ego and fear? I've
already given you the answer. Faith,
hope, and love. But let's examine what
this really means. Okay. All right. So,
uh can you continue uh Carol, please?
>> Verse 88.
Nor did he lower his eyes in shame
because he was the son of Petro
Benardon. Nor for the scorn and wonder
he aroused, but like a sovereign he
disclosed in full to innocent the
sternness of his rule. From him he had
the first seal of his order. And after
many of the poor had followed Francis
whose wondrous life was better sung by
glory's choir and the imperion the
sacred purpose of this chief of ch she
shepherds was then encircled with the
second crown by the eternal spirit
through Anorius
and after in his thirst for martyrdom
within the presence of the hottie sultan
he preached of Christ and those who
followed him. Okay. So, Francis is being
uh described as exemplar of faith, hope,
and love. Why? Because not only did he
embrace poverty,
but he went to the Islamic world
and tried to convert the sultan. Okay,
that is the exampler model of faith,
hope, and love. Okay, does that make
sense? Okay, keep this image in the back
of your mind. This man who's a Christian
from this backward place called Europe.
He goes to probably the wealthiest place
in the world and he tries to convince
the sultan that, hey, you're wrong.
You're worshiping the wrong god. And let
me tell you why. Okay. Uh, keep on
going.
Verse 103. By finding hearers who were
too unripe to be converted, he not
wasting time returned to harvest the
Italian fields. There on the naked crag
between Ardo and Tibar, he received the
final seal for from Christ. And this his
limbs bore for two years. When he who
destined Francis to such goodness was
pleased to draw him up to the reward
that he had won through his humility,
then to his brothers as to rightful
heirs, Francis commended his most
precious lady, and he bade them to love
her faithfully.
>> Okay. So, so, okay. So, you guys
understand what's happening, right?
Francis will die. He'll go to heaven to
to receive his just reward. He tells his
brothers, his entire followers to be
loyal to his wife. Right?
My wife is poverty. Now that I'm gone,
my only request, my last will testament
is for you to be loyal to take care of
my wife who's given me everything in
this world and who's helped me to ascend
to heaven. So, of course, what do they
do?
What do they do? Obviously,
uh yes,
>> they they're not disloyal. They abandon
poverty.
>> And and and and by how if you if you are
this brotherhood, the Francis order,
what's the easiest way for you to
abandon poverty?
>> Someone who are rich.
>> [laughter]
>> No, because they're all celibate, right?
This is Francis order. So, they're
supposed to marry poverty and so what do
they do? And and and it it's a loophole,
right? They they're not going to like,
you know what, screw this. Uh we're
going to marry rich people. Okay. But
there's a loophole. What what's what is
the loophole?
>> Oh, the loophole is actually really
famous. So like uh it used to be that
during the time when Francis was alive
when people give the Franciscan order a
town uh a house in town to live in. And
Francis just climbed up the roof and
started tearing off the shingles. And
the town was like stop. And Francis was
like no you're giving us a house. We
can't have that. Even if we share it, we
can't have that. And so the town told
Francis, okay, I guess we're lending you
the house. And Francis begrudgedly
agreed. So after he died, this kind of
went overboard like the Franciscans were
borrowing things left and right, left
and right and eventually they became the
like the other orders. But all of their
things are technically borrowed.
>> Okay. Well, they basically own property.
Okay. So let me ask you this question.
Why were the people giving them
property?
Why were people giving them property?
So did they say something like give us
um property and then you can perhaps
ascend to heaven or like
>> the say this. The friends would never
ever say this. Okay, they would never
say if you make me rich, I'll get I'll
make you go to heaven. Okay, that's not
what happened.
>> Like donate to our just cause.
>> No, they would never they would never
say that. So what would happen? Uh yes.
Yes. You go first and then you. Okay.
>> Yeah, you should be poor. So So I'll
I'll take your property from you.
>> No, they would never ever do that. Okay.
They would never do that. What happened?
>> They were actually inspirational. They
were really inspirational. Like rich
people, some people wanted to be
Franciscans, but they could feel like
they couldn't cut off their material
ties entirely. So, they give the
Franciscans on property.
>> Exactly. Do you understand? It's a
bribe, guys. Okay. If I'm rich, I have a
billion dollars and these guys are going
to heaven because they're poor. What
What I'm going to do? I'm going to bribe
these guys. Says, "Hey, I'll give you
half a mill. I'll give you like half a
billion dollars. I'll give you half my
wealth." Okay? I still keep a half a
billion. You get how good and we all go
to heaven, guys. What a great deal.
You understand?
That's what happened. They did not
intentionally try to become rich, but
they were forced to become rich because
everyone wanted to go to heaven. Okay,
the idea here is that money doesn't
really matter. It's salvation that
matters. They have the keys to heaven.
Everyone was like, "How much can I pay
for these keys?"
And for like no that's not how this
works guys okay this is not how it works
but if you are not Francis and you're
just this normal human being and and
people are offering you like billions
and billions of dollars
you it's hard for you to refuse okay and
that's and that's what happened
okay doesn't make sense guys okay the
would never ever say give me money and
you go to heaven that's what the pope
did Okay. But not the Franciscans.
>> All right. Yes.
>> I think the relationship between the
Franciscans and the Pope is really
interesting. On one hand, Francis was a
devout Catholic and he will never
contradict the Pope. In fact, he was
told by Catholic Central to maybe tone
the richest bad thing down a little bit
because you're making us look bad. And
Francis was like, "Okay." Also uh even
though Francis is widely known as a
peacemaker uh during the crusades he did
not speak up against the crusades and he
approved the crusades tacitly because
after all he was affiliated with the
church.
>> Okay. Yeah. So this is a very important
point. Okay. So what's happening in this
in this time is that there are a lot of
people who are opposed to the Catholic
church because the Catholic church is
filthy rich and they were like wait a
minute here Jesus was poor. He said,
"Don't be rich."
Um, and you guys are filthy rich. Okay?
And they were like ostentatious about
it, like you know, just go to go to
Rome, man. Okay? Go to the Vatican. It's
the wealthiest place in the world. Um,
so there's all this criticism and a way
for the Catholic Church to deal with
this criticism is to sponsor defenses in
order, right? as a way to co-opt these
people and show you see there are people
in the church who are dedicated to
poverty. So the Franciscans were a
useful political pawn
uh for the church to maintain
legitimacy. Okay. Right. So thank you
for that. All right. Let's keep on
going. [snorts]
Verse 115.
And when returning to its kingdom, his
bright soul wanted to set forth from her
bosom it for its body asked no other
buyer. Consider now that man who was a
colleague worthy of Francis with him in
high seas he kept the bark of Peter on
true course. Such was our patriarch.
Thus,
>> uh, he's referring to Paul, by the way.
Okay, Paul. Keep on going.
>> Such was our patriarch. Thus you can see
that those who follow him as he
commands, as cargo carry worthy
merchandise. But now his flock is grown
so greedy for new nourishment that it
must wander far in search of strange and
distant grazing lands. And as his sheep,
remote and vagabond, stray farther from
his side, at their return into the fold,
their lack of milk is greater. Though
there are some indeed who fearing harm
stay near the shepherd, they are few in
number. To call them would require
little cloth. Now if my words are not
too dim and distant, if you have
listened carefully to them, if you can
call to mind what has been said, then
part of what you wish to know is
answered. For you will see the splinters
on the plant and see what my correction
meant. where one may fatten well if one
does not stray off.
>> Okay. All right. So um this creates a
central dilemma. Okay. These are people
the Franciscans
who have the most noble purpose. Okay.
To spread the message of Jesus to bring
hope and salvation to the poorest people
to embrace poverty. These are the best
Catholics.
But there are two central issues. The
first is their ego and their fear,
right? The fact that to truly embrace
poverty the way that Francis did, you
have to abandon society. And no one
wants to do that, right? It's a social
death. And you're afraid of what it
means to be poor. So the ego and the
fear. But another issue is that once you
truly embrace poverty and you are seen
as holy, the entire world wants to
co-opt you. They want to bribe you. They
want to give you money so that they can
share in your holiness. And over time
that accumulates and you just become
just as corrupt as everyone else. Okay.
So these are the two central dilemmas
and the question then is
how do you overcome
this situation.
How do you
how can you actually bring salvation to
humanity if the if there are these
constraints? Okay. One is our own
psychological constraint of ego and
fear. Another is just the social
constraint. Okay. how how anything
that's valuable people will try to buy
out. Okay. Do you understand the
dilemma? Right? Okay. And this is the
situation that Dante is facing in
medieval Europe in the year 1300 to 1321
when he's writing divine comedy. Okay.
Any questions before we move on?
Okay. All right. Let's move on to 12,
please. Okay. And now and now we are
going to meet one of our who's going to
talk about the Dominican order and then
he's going to criticize the Franciscan
order. Okay. No, sorry. No, no. He's
he's he's going to embrace the the
Dominican order and criticize the
Franciscan order. Okay.
Oh, wait. Sorry. Um something that I've
forgot to mention is that um the reason
so for St. Thomas Acquaintus, the reason
why he thinks that the uh Dominican
order became corrupt is eventually they
had too much power, right? The Dominican
order are the Jesuits of the time.
They're committed to learning. They're
committed to uh economic inquiry. But
the Catholic Church uses them as
inquisitors to maintain orthodoxy
throughout the um throughout Europe.
Okay? So they spread far and wide and
accumulate too much power and that
ultimately corrupts them. Okay. Does
that make sense guys? Okay. All right.
Uh now now we talk about the Dominicans.
Okay.
>> Kto 12.
No sooner had the blessed flame begun to
speak its final word than the millstone
of holy lights began to turn. But it was
not yet done with one full revolution
before another ring surrounded it. And
motion matched with motion song with
song. A song that's sung by those sweet
instruments surpasses so our muses and
our sirens as first light does the light
that is reflected. Just as concentric
like in color, two rainbows will curve
their way through a thin cloud when Juno
has commanded her handmade. The outer
rainbow echoing the inner much like the
voice of one. The wandering nymph whose
love consumed as sun consumes the mist.
And those two boughs let people here
foretell by reason of the pact God made
with Noah that flood will never strike
the world again. So the two garlands of
those everlasting roses circled around
us and so did the outer circle mime the
inner ring when dance and jubilation
festival of song and flame that answered
flame of light with light of gladness
and benevolence in some s in one same
instant with one will fell still just as
the eyes when moved by their desire can
only close and open in accord than from
the heart of one of the lights there
came a voice and as I turned toward it I
seemed a needle turning to the pole star
and it began the love that makes me fair
draws me to speak about the other leader
because of whom my own was so praised
here where one is it is right to
introduce the other side by side they
fought so may they share in glory and
together gleam Christ's army whose
rearming cost so dearly was slow,
uncertain of itself, and scanty behind
its enzyme. When the emperor, who rules
forever, helped his ranks in danger,
only out of his grace and not their
merits. And as was said, he then
sustained his bride, providing her with
two who could revive a scraggling
people, champions who would by doing and
by preaching bring new life.
>> Okay. All right. So again, the bride is
Catholic Church and the two champions
are Francis and Dominic. Okay. Uh, keep
on going.
>> Verse 46. In that part of the West,
where gentle Sephir rises to open those
new leaves in which Europe appears,
reclothed, not far from where, behind
the waves that beat upon the coast. The
sun grown weary from its lengthy course,
at times conceals itself from all men's
eyes. There karoga blessed by fortune
sits under the eeges of the mighty
shield on which the lion loses and
prevails. Within its walls were born the
loving vassel of Christian faith, the
holy athlete, one kind to his own and
harsh to enemies. No sooner was his mind
created than it was so full of living
force that it still in his mother's womb
made her prophetic. Then at the sacred
font where faith and he brought mutual
salvation as their dowy the rights of
their espouso was were complete.
>> Okay. All right. So so the idea here is
that Francis married poverty. Dominique
will marry faith. Okay. All right. Keep
on going.
>> Verse 64. The lady who had given the
ascent from for him saw in a dream
astonishing fruit that would spring from
him and from his heirs and that his name
might echo what he was. A spirit moved
from here to have him called by the
possessive of the one by whom he was
possessed completely. Dominic became his
name. I speak of him as one whom Christ
chose as the worker in his garden. He
seemed the fitting messenger and servant
of Christ. The very first love that he
showed was the first injunction Christ
had given. His nurse would often find
him on the ground alert and silent in a
way that said, "It is for this that I
have come. Truly his father was Feliche
and his m mother Jovana, if her name
interpreted, is in accord with what has
been asserted. Not for the world, but
for which men now travail along Toade
Deo's way, or Aans, but through his love
of the true mana, he became in a brief
time so great a teacher that he began to
oversee the vineyard that withers when
neglected by its keeper. And from the
seat that once was kinder to the
righteous poor, and now has gone astray,
not in itself, but in its occupant. He
did not ask to offer two or three for
six nor four vacant benefits nor decimus
qualarum
de but pleaded for the right to fight
against the airing world to serve the
seed from which there grew the 420
plants that ring you.
>> Okay. All right. So, okay. So, let's go
into the history of the Dominicans.
Dominicans were founded for a very
specific purpose. So um at this time in
Europe there's a major threat to the
Catholic Church and it's called the
Cathars. Okay, the Cathars
[clears throat]
the Cathars. Okay. Um and to deal with
the Cathars and they are in southern
France in a place called Albanese. The
Catholic Church lo lot la call the alben
the albengian
crusade. Okay the idea is that these
catholic cathars are what we call
gnostics. What are gnostics? Gnostics is
are are people who believe in the ideas
that Dante believes. Okay. That we have
a direct connection to god uh who is the
monad the source and that this material
world doesn't really matter. What
matters is our spiritual life. And these
cathars are impossible to deal with
because they're not afraid to die. In
fact, they welcome death. Right? Before
the Catholic Church is like, "If you
don't obey us, we'll burn you at the
stake." And the Cath and the Cathars are
like, "Fine. I'm happy to burn at the
stake." Okay? So the uh Catholic Church
launches these crusades against the
Cathars who are who are um uh in the
southern France and the Cathars are not
afraid to die and they are so holy and
they're so inspirational that the
community who are by the way majority
Catholic they rally behind the Cathars
and protect the carer's right to
um [clears throat] believe in what and
what they believe. Okay. Um the cath the
Catholics are so inspirational that in
one famous instance when the Catholic
army the crusaders has basically um
surrounded a fortress. Okay. And again
what's really important to understand is
that the majority of people fighting for
the Cathars are themselves Catholic.
And so what happens is this fortress is
is about to fall. [clears throat] And
the
um commander of the Catholic army says
to the Cathars, "We only want you guys,
the Catholic people who are protecting
you, we'll let them live."
And [clears throat]
the Catholic people protecting the
Cathars said fine we will convert okay
we will become Cathars ourselves
we will die with you okay so that's how
inspirational they were so the Catholic
church is like what are we going to do
okay because yes we can possibly
step them out, but this is embarrassing
for us and their example is going to
possibly overthrow us. So they create
the dome order in order to deal with the
Cathar threat, the the Albian crusade.
And the idea is that you cannot kill
these people. What you do is you
re-educate these people. Okay? So rather
than use the sword, they use the pen. So
the do the the ordered would go into a
village and there's only about like 1%
who are cathars, right? But you just
figure out who they are and they would
interrogate everyone
and quite honestly that worked because
in inter in interrogation
you could figure out who the Cathars
were because there were inconsistencies
in the stories, right? And then once you
isolate them, then you could then
re-educate them. And that and that's the
idea behind the Dominican order. And as
you can imagine, the Dominicans fought
themselves. They were warriors for
Christ. That their mission was not to
kill people. Their mission was to show
them the error of their thinking. Okay?
Re-education,
enlightenment.
And through that, the Catholic Church
was able to stamp out the Catholar
threat. Okay, does that make sense,
guys? Okay.
Any questions about that?
Okay, let's let's keep on going.
Verse 97. Then he with both his learning
and his zeal, and with his apostolic
office, like a torrent hurdled from a
mountain source, coursed, and his
impetus with greatest force, struck
where the thickets of the heretics
offered the most resistance. And from
him there sprang the streams with which
the Catholic garden has found abundant
watering, so that its saplings have more
life, more green. If such was one wheel
of the chariot in which the holy church
in her defense taking the field defeated
enemies within, then you must see the
excellence of him, the other wheel whom
Thomas praised so graciously before I
made my entry. And yet the track traced
by the outer rim of that wheel is
abandoned now as in a cask of wine when
crust gives way to mold. His family
which once advanced with steps that
followed his footprints has now turned
back. Its fortoot now seeks the foot
that lags. And soon we are to see at
harvest time the poor grain gathered
where the tears will be denied a place
within the bin and weep. I do admit that
if one were to search our volume leaf by
leaf, he might still read one page with
I am as I always was. But those of
Aquasparta or Casale who read our rule
are either given to escape in it or
making it too strict. I am the living
light of Bonavour of Banora in high
offices. I always put the left hand
interests last.
>> Okay. The left hand interest what what
he's saying is that the Catholic Church
is very corrupt. They are always doing
left-hand interests. Okay. The left hand
just means what whatever is sinister.
Um, and I am the most pure. I am the
most just official. Okay, keep keep on
going.
>> Verse 130. Illuminato and Augustine are
here. They were among the first unshot
poor brothers to wear the cord becoming
friends of God. Hugh of St. Victor 2 is
here with them. Peter of Spain who with
his 12 books glows on earth below and
Peter book devourer. Nathan the prophet
Anom and Chrysm the metrop metropolitan
and that donadus who dame to deal with
that art which comes first. ravenous too
in here and at my side shines the
Calabrian Abbott Jacan who had the gift
of the prophetic the prophetic spirit to
this my praise of such a paladin the
glowing courtesy and the discerning
language of Thomas urged me on and
stirred with me the souls that form this
company
>> okay all right so okay so again to
summarize we've we learned about the
first of order and we learned about the
Dominican order. They both started out
as just good and righteous. But over
time, both will become corrupt. Okay?
The Franciscans become corrupt because
people want to give them property. Okay?
The Dominicans become corrupt because
they have too much power. Okay? They
have power of life. They have the power
of life and death over people and they
spread throughout Europe in order to be
the army of the Catholic Church. Okay?
Okay. So you can imagine it is it's a
similar situation where the rich are
bribing them in order to curry favor
with them. Okay. To settle local scores
to gain a place in heaven to influence
um internal politics. Okay. All right.
Uh yes. [snorts]
So in in this um in this section we see
that they see that the Dominicans are in
Paradiso. If the Dominicans were
converting the Cathas,
what what is Dante's actually thought of
the Cathars? Does he think they were
good or bad? Okay. So, we will never
know what Dante thought of the Cathars.
Okay. Um he knows what happened, but he
probably believes that they were a
heretical sect because that was the
official um um doctrine. Okay. And
remember at this time in history, Donnie
has much greater problems to deal with.
Okay. The fact that brother's killing
brother, the fact that the Catholic
Church is so corrupt, those are those
are his concerns. Does that make sense?
Uh, yes.
>> I've noticed that this is something that
Dante likes to do. Like he like he likes
to roll call people. Like uh I remember
uh like reading about uh Dante roll
calling people in hell. Like he
condemned a bunch of people who are
still alive to hell. And there's a place
in hell for them. And basically, he's
making a goody list and bad list here.
Can I say it like that?
>> Yes. Exactly. Okay. Yeah. Right.
[clears throat] Um, this is a way for
him to try to structure the world. Um,
and also to make sense of what's going
on in the world. Okay. Basically, from
his perspective, um, he has a power to
judge people. So those that are doing
wrong, he can put in hell. those that he
knows that did good. For example, his
patrons, he puts into heaven. Okay. All
right. Um, okay. Another thing that I
want to talk about is we assume that
whatever he writes is intentional,
meaning it's a conscious decision on his
part to frame the way things are. Okay.
But
a lot of poetry is subconscious because
you are channeling the divine. Does that
make sense? So we can objectively as
critics, as readers, make some
historical parallels between what he's
saying. We know. Okay. But it could be
possible
that
um his understanding of the history is
different from our understanding of the
history. It's also possible that he
really didn't know about the Cathars
because they were suppressed. Okay, we
know about the Cthars because of our own
research. So, does that make sense to
you guys? All right, we're assuming that
Dante knows what he's actually singing,
but it may not. It may just be complete
inspiration
and we as critics are able to look back
and said, "Oh, I see the connection
here, but he may not be conscious of
this information."
Okay, does that make sense? All right.
So, so that's why it's impossible to say
what is his intention because he himself
may not know what his intention is. He's
just a poet. He is a prophet for God.
He's just speaking what he believes to
be true even though he himself may not
know actually what he's saying.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> Do we have any like Costki wrote to his
brother all the time and he's like this
is what I'm thinking. Is there any
letters that exist of Dante?
>> Um yeah. So there are lots of documents.
Um so Dante was a published poet before
Divine Comedy. Divine Comedy is his last
act but he's written also many different
different works as well. And you know,
it's really strange because
none of his works received the same
acclaim as Divine Comedy, but he was
sure he was the greatest poet in the
world. And he was sure that in his
lifetime he'd be recognized as the
greatest poet in uh the world.
Excuse me.
get what he wanted.
>> Um, well, what happens when we read The
Inferno, what what's happening is that
he places himself in with the same
status as Virgil and the other great
Latin epic poets. Okay. So, already he's
conceived himself as a legendary poet
even though he's not that famous at this
point. Even though he's not recognized
as the greatest poet at this at this
time, he is confident that that he will
be recognized in his lifetime doesn't
work out that way. He will die after he
finish divine comedy and people will
recognize Divine Comedy as a work of
genius after he dies, but not during his
lifetime. Okay. Um All right.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh sorry, I have a question. Uh I just
uh I just question uh you know, do you
think that you really think that he's a
point? because you know
yes the people paid money for for him to
be a point or it just people right now
we thought that he he was point so what
I mean is that what a purpose of of his
writing if there's nobody who paid money
for for for him to do that then there
must be some purpose for himself to to
write down such long poem you know we
can call a masterpiece or he can just
write by themselves just to not worry or
care about the readers is that what you
mean Um, okay. Uh, let me let me ask you
a question. Has there been anyone in
history who has been a great poet, who
has chosen to be a great poet?
You are not you don't choose to be a
poet. You don't choose to be a prophet.
You are chosen by God. Okay? And God
channels his power through you. And how
do we how do people know that this is a
great poet? How do we how how do we
know?
Excuse me.
>> By reading their work.
>> Yeah. But but so we we can read a lot of
work, but how do we know what's
what's great and what's not? If if the
work persists throughout the course of
history like over time, if it survives.
>> Yeah. But but but how does it survive
over time? I guess people have to like
maintain it, right? citation, you know,
he
>> No, no, no, no. I think we just know if
if the work is is great, we just know
the work is great. Like it's
>> Yeah, but but how do we know?
>> We just know it.
>> No, but I mean why? How?
>> Like the contents have been proven by
time.
>> This is not a hard question. Okay. Yes.
>> It resonates with our experience. And
what do we call this?
truth and beauty, right? You understand?
Like if people read the Nikolai and they
think, "Oh my god, it made me cry. Oh my
god, that's so beautiful." No one would
bother to keep it around, right? It's
truth and beauty that makes Divine
Comedy a great work of poetry. It's the
same. It's no difference from like why
do you go to a concert and pay 50 bucks
or I I I've never been to concert. I
don't know how much they cost. Okay, but
I know you're sitting around with 10,000
people. It's a pain in the ass. But why
are you doing this? Because a singer,
whoever he or she is, moves you to
tears. Because it resonates with you. Do
you understand? Okay, we are looking at
divine comedy from an intellectual
analytical perspective. But it's able to
be so powerful because first and
foremost, it resonates because it speaks
beauty and truth. Do you understand? And
beauty and truth can only come from God.
Try to do you understand? Okay.
Only a human being by telling God can
create such truth and beauty in the
world. And only a person can do this. If
you get two people to try to do this, it
won't work. Okay? Try it. Try to get two
people to write a poem together. It
sucks.
It has to be a person channeling the
monad, the source. And then you know
it's beautiful because everyone who
reads it is moved to tears because it's
beautiful, right? No different from a
painting. Why do we have um why do we
celebrate certain paintings? Because
they're more beautiful than others.
Okay, this is not a random thing.
Does that make sense?
Okay, any more questions before we move
on?
Okay, so let's go to Kanto 17. Okay.
And um we don't we also don't have time
to read Kel 17 but but I will introduce
some basic ideas for Kel 17 and then we
will go into Kel 17. Um
and so Dante has a series of questions
that he must resolve before he can meet
God. Okay, he is going to meet God. That
is the purpose of divine comedy. is a
pilgrim's journey into
um the heart of the universe, the soul
of the universe
and he is full of ego and his fear full
of fear. Okay, the ego is like I'm the
greatest poet in the world. Why doesn't
people recognize that I'm the greatest
poet in the world? The fear is I've been
exiled from Florence
and
um where does my life go from from here?
I have a family. How can I feed my
family?
I have no source of income because the
people in Florence who exile me have
stolen everything from me. Okay? I've
got nothing in this world.
And so I know my mission is to write the
Divine Comedy. I know my heart. That's
what my mission is. But the reality
around me is like I'm in exile. I have
kids. I have no property. What am I
going to do now?
Also, I look around the world. I look
around the world and I start out with
the Gves and we defeat the Gil
Gilibbeans, but the GW fought amongst
themselves.
So,
what's the hope for this world if all we
do is just fight for power? I also think
about the Franciscans and the Dominicans
and they started out great but then they
became everyone like everyone else.
Okay. So what is the point of my
existence? Why am I writing Divine
Comedy?
Is there any hope for humanity? Is there
any hope for us?
Okay. So what's going to happen is that
Dante must reserve these fears, these
doubts before he can actually meet God.
Because if you're coming to meet God
from a place of ego and fear, you're not
going to meet God. Okay? You're just
not. You don't see God.
So the way he does this is that he will
in heaven
meet his ancestor or grandfather. I
can't actually remember the if it's
great grandfather or great-grandfather
but but but it's it's an ancestor. Okay.
What the answer is going to do is
reassure him
by telling him the history of his
family, the lineage, okay, where they
came from, all the great deeds that the
family has done throughout the course of
history.
And then what the grandfather's gonna do
is give Dante the prophecy. Okay. Um
where your life is going to go.
Why would this be reassuring to Dante?
Why would knowing your family history be
reassuring to Dante?
You You are in You are at a stage in
your life when all hope is broken.
You're in exile. You're poor. But
hearing the your history, the family,
your family history where you came from
does give you hope. Why? I guess
>> because it gives you something to hold
on to. Like they can take away
everything you own in this world, but
your connection to your ancestors and
the great deeds of your ancestors. They
will never go away. They cannot take
that away.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, what this is saying is
that you'll be remembered for your
actions. Okay. Just as your the actions
of your father were remembered, just as
the actions of your grandfather
remembered. Okay? That's what you will
leave to the world. Not your wealth,
not your achievements, but your actions.
Okay? Your actions will be celebrated,
your actions will be remembered. Anyone
else? What why would this what will this
matter?
>> Uh also it gives a sense of cycle where
like even if times are bad then like
just with time it gets better.
>> Yeah. So there's a plan in motion,
right?
>> What so by by saying like you know this
is what your grandfather did, this is
your father did, you're you're saying
that there is a plan and this is all
part of your destiny. Dante,
you came to this point because it was
planned from the beginning and your
family was just enacting out the plan
and now you have come to this point and
you must do your part as well. Okay. And
that is very reassuring I would think.
Right.
What? Why else?
>> Yes.
>> So, I'm just going to add on to that and
say that I think at least I think during
this time like ancestry was um seen as
to be like very important and like your
ancestors were seen uh to be like much
wiser than you were. So I think that
just um Dante by listening to his
ancestors reassure him like he felt that
yeah I'm reassured because I trust these
people a lot and there they definitely
know more than
>> Yeah. Exactly. Okay. That's a really
good point. Okay. So yes, the ancestors
are giving you support. Yes. Yes.
>> And by um by looking at their um
achievement, their endeavors, you can
also see what they've yet to achieve.
And maybe that's for and that's how you
connect the dots. That's how you realize
so this is the part that I would do that
they didn't manage to
>> yes achieve.
>> You're part of a family and you have a
responsibility to do your part right you
have to add to us. So yes you have to
find common and you'll probably die
afterwards. You won't achieve any fame
but with your achievement will add to
our family legacy right that's your
responsibility.
So what's happening is that just the
idea that you're part of a family
legacy, it's removing the ego and fear
from him, right? Okay. It's cleansing
him. Any other comments or thoughts?
Okay. So when we come back from the
break, we're going to read not the
family history. It's a bit long, but
we'll read the prophecy
that the grandfather tells Dante. Okay.
And so something to keep in mind is it's
really complicated. Okay. Uh but but I
want you to keep this in mind. So
Dante is dies in 1321. Okay. He actually
finished the Divine Comedy in 1321.
What's interesting is that
the Divine Comedy is set in the year
1300, Easter Sunday. Okay. He tells us
this in the infernal. Okay. So in other
words, he already has the benefit of
hindsight. He already knows what's going
to happen to him. Okay. But in but he
sets his character in the year 1300 and
then his grandfather will tell Dante
what will happen in the year
1302. Okay. 1302 is when Dante is exiled
from Florence and this marks a um
traumatic event in his life. Okay. So
think think about this where Don is
writing in 1321. He already knows what's
already happened but he set his
character
in the year 1300 so that his grandfather
can tell him what will happen two years
from now. Okay. Two years from from now.
Okay. And and and and that is the
setting for uh candle 17 which we'll
read after the break. Any questions
guys? Yes. Uh you said that to connect
with God you need to let go of fear and
ego but then how can he do so in heaven
which is like already with God right
>> but he's not in heaven
>> didn't you say that he let go of fear uh
by talking with his ancestors
>> right okay so um okay so so to
understand this is that this is a uh
literary conceit okay the way he lets go
of his ego and fear is by writing the
vine comedy,
right? And in Divine Comedy, um the
scene that he sets to help us appreciate
how he's able to let go of his ego and
fear is the meeting with his grandfather
in heaven. Does does that make sense?
>> Okay.
>> So, that means in the beginning of the
writing, he's not quite yet like
enlightenment, right? Like to a state of
enlightenment.
>> That's right. Okay. That that's a really
that's a really important thing to
appreciate where maybe from an early age
he's able to to conceive the divine
comedy. Okay. But the very process of
writing it is also uh revelatory and
enlightening. Do you understand? All
right. Um and so he will change as a
person through the process of reading
divine comedy. the same thing as reading
divine comedy where I'm sure like by
reading it you yourself are going
through a spiritual and emotional
alchemy right you're thinking much more
deeply about who you are you're thinking
much more deeply about your relationship
with the world and maybe your heart is
opening up well it's the same thing or
it's obviously the same if you write the
thing right because what's happening is
that the poetry is a revelation from God
okay it is you are co-creating the
process, but what you're really doing is
you're just a scribe for God, right?
That does that make sense, guys? All
right. Okay. So, we'll take a break.
We'll come back at one o'clock. Okay.
All right. Thanks, guys.
Okay. All right, guys. Uh, we are live.
Um, first of all, I want to thank so
much, Carol, and our team. Um there are
some comments online talking about the
sound quality and the um video
resolution quality and Carol and her
team worked really hard yesterday and
now it's and now a new version is
uploaded complete with better sound and
video quality. So thank you so much
Carol and and your team for your self
selfless dedication to promoting Dante
in the world. Okay. So what what I will
do now is discuss the central conflict
which is how does Dante reconcile
his divine mission which is to be the
prophet poet for the monad with the fact
that his life really really sucks. Um in
1302 he was exiled from his hometown of
Florence where he's been his family has
been there for generations. Uh he loves
the place. um he loses everything. He
loses all his property, all all his
wealth because of his exile. And now
he's just fooling around. Okay. So, how
does he reconcile this pain, this agony,
this suffering with his large divine
mission? And here, what he's going to do
is he's going to uh re-imagine
um Virgil the Iniad. Okay? So, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to summarize
for you the plot of the uh Iniad. We
should read it together. We don't have
time, but um for for the sake of the
conversation today, I'm just going to
give you a brief summary of the um
Iniad. Okay. So, this is Virgil. And for
about a thousand years, this is the
greatest epic poem of the Western
tradition. And if you're an educated
person, you have to read it. It is the
Bible. Okay? is actually much more
important than the Bible. So the so the
main character is Inas
and Inas is a prince of Troy and like
Dante he loves Troy. They've been his
family has been there for generations.
It is the greatest city in the world.
Unfortunately the Greeks have to come
and destroy it. Okay. And um Inas has to
watch his city being destroyed by the
Greeks. This is Trojan War, of course.
They sneak in because of the Trojan
horse. And Inas wants to die trying to
save uh Troy. But his mother um Venus
appears before him and says, "No, Inias,
you have a higher mission. You have a
higher calling. You, your son, will be
destined to found the greatest empire in
the world called Rome. Okay? Rome will
be the new Troy. Troy must be destroyed
in order for Rome to rise and Rome will
be the end of history. It will be the
greatest empire in all of human history.
So, Inis is like fine, okay? Because
he's been ordered by the gods. And so he
and his family and the followers, they
get on ships and they sail to Italy
where they're supposed to found the new
empire of Rome. They get shipwrecked and
uh they end up in Carthage. And in
Carthage,
Inas there falls in love with the queen
Ditto
and Inas is really really happy in
Carthage.
and Carthage is this new city that's
being built and um Inas sees his life
being here. The gods get angry at him
and said, "Inas, you idiot. We told you
to Italy, not Carthage. Get your ass
moving." So Inas is like, "Fine,
whatever." ever. So, he keeps on moving,
but now he's like really really angry
because his home Troy was destroyed and
then he falls in love with Ditto in
Carthage [clears throat] and and the
gods kick him out. Okay, so he's really
confused. So, what he does is he goes
into the underworld
[clears throat]
where he meets his father, Inius. Okay,
and his father just died because Inius
is going to tell him why this is
happening.
what what the gods have planned for you.
And when in his talks to inas, what
happens is that the prophecy
becomes the history of Rome.
And
in is told that when you go to Rome,
your son will found a new people, the
Romans. The Romans will slowly expand
across the Italian peninsula. then they
will conquer Carthage and then conquer
all the Mediterranean. They will become
the greatest empire in human history. So
it's it's basically just the same thing
as what Justinian told us, right? Um
then you you have Julius Caesar will
give rise to Augustus Caesar. And when
this happens, when Rome becomes an
empire,
it is the end of history. Humanity will
be saved. Um heaven will come to earth
and peace will reign forever. the Pax
Romana. Okay. And this is why things had
to happen the way they had they
happened. Troy was destroyed for a
reason to found Rome.
Um Inias had to go on this long pavement
journey in order to to build a
foundation stone for the greatest empire
in human history. Okay. And obviously
when Inas hears this, he's like, "Yes,
now I understand. Now I can fully commit
to my mission." So he goes to Italy
um where he uh fights uh Churnis. Okay.
And then uh it ends with his victory and
now Rome can be born. Okay. So the Iniad
it's basically the bible Roman Empire.
It explains where Rome came from, why
Rome is the greatest empire in the world
and where Rome is going. Okay, does that
make sense? So, we're going to take this
uh plotline from the Iniad and compare
it to how Dante
um rewrites this. Okay? And you're going
to see a massive contrast because here
in the Eniad, the prophecy is one of
triumph, one of glory.
But in Dante's uh prophecy, it's
completely different. Okay. So, this is
KTO 17 and we're going to read
um
uh Dante's grandfather telling him what
lies in store for him when he leaves
heaven, returns to the real world, what
awaits him. Okay. All right. Uh
>> okay.
>> Please read.
>> Like the one who still makes fathers
wary of sons. When he heard when he had
heard insinuations and he to be assured
came to Clemen, such was I and such was
I seen to be by Beatress and by the holy
lamp that earlier had shifted place for
me. Therefore my lady said to me,
display the flame of your desire that it
may be seen well stamped with your
internal seal. Not that we need to know
what you'd reveal, but that you learn
the way that would disclose your thirst
and you be quenched by what we pour. Oh
my dear root, who since you rise so
high, can see the point in which all
times are present. For just as earthly
minds are able to see that two obtuse
angles cannot be contained in a
triangle, you can see contingent things
before they come to be. While I was in
the company of Virgil, both on the
mountain that heals souls and when
descending to the dead world, what I
heard about my future life were grievous
words. Although against the blows of
chance, I feel myself as firmly planted
as a cube.
>> Okay. Stop. Okay. All right. So, what
he's referring to is the fact that in
inferno and in purgatory, Virgil was his
guide. And during this journey uh Dante
met individuals who would give him
glimpses into his future. Okay. And this
is the final prophecy.
Keep on going.
Verse 25. Thus my desire would be
appeased if I might know what fortune is
approaching me. The arrow one foresees
arrives more gently.
So did I speak to the same living light
that spoke to me before. As Beatus had
wi wished, what was my wish was now
confessed, not with the maze of words
that used to snare the fools upon this
earth before the lamb of God who takes
away our sins was slain, but with words
plain and unamiguous, that loving
father, hidden yet revealed by his own
smile, replied contingency, while not
extending past the book in which your
world of matter has been written and the
internal vision all depicted.
But this does not imply necessity. Just
as a ship that sails downstream is not
determined by the eye that watches it.
And from that vision, just as from an
Oregon that year receives a gentle
harmony, what time prepares for you
appears to me.
Hippolitus was forced to leave his
Athens because of his stepmother,
faithless, fierce, and so must you
depart from Florence. Okay. So, Hippotus
was um um the son of Thesus who uh was
exiled
um unjustly. So, the idea is that yes,
Dante, unfortunately, when you go home,
what will happen to you is that you'll
be exiled from Florence unjustly. Okay?
They will do a terrible wrong to you,
but there's nothing you can do about it.
That's all part of the plan. Keep on
going.
>> Verse 49. This is willed already sought
for soon to be accomplished by the one
who plans and plots where every day
Christ is both sold and bought.
>> Okay. So, uh the man who will plan and
plot is the pope. Okay. So, the pope is
going to plot your exile and the removal
of your faction from Florence so that
you can never ever return. Okay, this is
the pope. He is corrupt. He buys and
sells um salvation. Keep on going.
>> Verse 52. The blame, as usual, will be
cried out against the injured party, but
just vengeance will serve as witness to
the truth that wields it. You shall
leave everything you love most dearly.
This is the arrow that the bow of exile
shoots first. You are to know the bitter
taste of others bread, how salt it is,
and know how hard a path it is for one
who goes descending and ascending others
dares.
>> Okay. All right. So, this is the
complete opposite of the vision, the
prophecy in the Iniad, right? Where Inis
is told about the glory that awaits
Rome. And here it's complete opposite
where Donnie is told, um, yeah, the only
thing that awaits you is exile. uh
you'll be blamed for the exile. You lose
everything and you will depend on the
mercy, the generosity of others. In
other words, you're going to be a beggar
all your life, Dante. You'll be a beggar
until the end of your life. Uh yes.
>> Could this be seen as drawing a parallel
between himself and the experiences of
uh that guy Anus, I think his name is
Anas from from Troy, and the suffering
of Christ. like could he be drawing this
comparison that he is suffering to bring
about greatness later?
>> Um yeah that's exactly the parallel. So,
so you say two things. Okay. Yes,
clearly he is referencing uh Inias and
his journey and the prophecy from the
Inadan. Okay. Because the Inian is
basically his template to write the
Divine Comedy. But you also point out
that
Jesus is not really mentioned
in the Divine Comedy, guys, right? He's
referenced, but he's not mentioned
direct. Well, he is mentioned directly,
but he doesn't appear in Divine Comedy,
right? And so you can make the
imaginative leap that Dante is really
presenting himself as a Christ figure in
a divine comedy. The one who must
suffer, the one who must die in order to
bring about salvation in the world.
Okay. So, so yeah, thank you for that.
Okay. Any more questions, guys?
All right. Uh let's keep on going.
>> Verse 61.
And what will be most hard for you to
bear will be the scheming, senseless
company that is to share your fall into
this valley. Against you they will be
insane, completely ungrateful and
profane. And yet soon after not you, but
they will have their brows blood dread
of their insensate acts. The proof will
be in the effects. And thus your honor
will be best kept if your party is
yourself. your first refuge and your
first inn shall be the courtesy of the
great Lombard. He who on the latter
bears the sacred bird.
>> Okay, so when Don is exiled, he's exiled
with his political faction, right? The
uh white Gves. And obviously when their
faction, they're angry about this. They
want vengeance. So they're plotting how
to get back and kill their enemies, the
Black Gelves. And what uh the
grandfather is saying to Dante is do not
partake in this politics. These people
have gone insane with hatred and uh
blood lust. Okay? They can only end up
dead. You have to not only live in
poverty, not only do you must you be a
beggar, but you must abandon everyone
you know in order for you to seek the
true path. Okay? This is not just exile.
It is also isolation. It doesn't make
sense. All right. But at the same time,
you will find generous patrons who will
give you food and housing and that is
your salvation. Uh yes,
>> I think something else that he gives up
is vengeance. like uh I know that the
urge to avenge yourself is extremely
strong and it will be hard giving his
anger to give up in vengeance but the
truth is like passion is like a cup
within us and a cup can only hold so
much water. So if you fill the cup with
hatred with vengeance then you have no
place that for God and what Dante is
doing is clearing out the hatred the
vengeance so he has more place in his
cup for God. Well, yeah. Okay. So, so
[clears throat] let's be clear, okay?
You're absolutely right in that he needs
to clear his hatred. He needs to clear
his vengeance. At the same time, we we
need to recognize that um when he goes
in exile, when he go becomes isolated,
when he when he is dependent on the
mercy and charity of others, that only
makes him even more angry and vengeful
and hateful, right? So then the question
then is how can he go about dissipating
and planting himself all this hatred,
anger and vengeance. The answer of
course is
>> by riding the inferno.
>> By writing the inferno, by going on this
journey into hell to see that hatred,
vengeance can only lead you into hell.
Okay? It's something that he must
experience for himself in order to
cleanse himself. That's why you must
first go to hell before you go to heaven
because you must experience for yourself
that anger and hatred can only lead in
one direction. Okay. All right. Let's
keep on going. [clears throat]
Verse 73.
And so benign will be his care for you
that with you too in giving and in
asking that shall be first which is with
others last. You shall beside him see
one who at birth had so received the
seal of this strong star that what he
does will be remarkable. People have yet
to notice him because he is a boy. For
nine years and no more have these
spheres wheeled around him. But before
the gone gs the noble Henry some sparks
will have will have marked the virtue of
the Lombard hard labor and his disregard
for silver.
>> Okay. Okay, so now he's just sucking up
to his patron, right? He he's in exile.
His patron is the one who is financing
the writing of Divine Comedy. He's
saying what a great guy this guy is.
He's selfless. He he he will he will he
will do great things. Okay. Uh keep on
going.
>> Verse 85. His generosity is yet to be so
notable that even enemies will never
hope to treat it silently. Put trust in
him and in his benefits. His gifts will
bring much metamorphosis.
Rich men and beggars will exchange their
states. What I tell you about him you
will bear, inscribed within your mind,
but hide it there. And he told things
beyond belief, even for those who will
yet see them. Then he added, "Son, these
are glosses of what you had heard. These
are the snares that hide beneath brief
ears. Yet I'd not have you envying your
neighbors. Your life will long outlast
the punishment that is to fall upon
their treacheries.
After that holy soul had with a silence
showed he was freed from putting in the
woof across the web whose warp I set for
him. I like a man who doubting craves
for counsel from one who sees and
rightly wills and loves. replied to him.
I clearly see my father how time is
hurrying toward me in order to deal me
such a blow as would be most grievous
for him who is not set for it. Thus it
is right to arm myself with foresight
that if I lose the place most dear I may
not lose the rest through what my poems
say. down in the world of endless
bitterness and on the mountain from
whose lovely peak I was drawn upward by
my lady's eyes and afterward from light
to light in heaven I learned that which
if I retell it must for many have a
taste too sharp too harsh yet I if I am
a timid friend of truth I fear that I
may lose my life among those who will
call this present ancient times the
light in which there smiled the treasure
I had found within
first began to dazzle as would a golden
mirror in the sun. Then it replied,
"A conscience that is dark, either
through its or through another shame,
and deed will find that what you speak
is harsh. Nevertheless, all falsehood
set aside, let all that you have seen be
manifest, and let them scratch wherever
it may itch.
>> [clears throat]
>> For if at the first taste your words
molest, they will when they have been
digested and as living nourishment, as
does the wind, so shall your outcry do.
The wind that sends its roughest blows
against the highest peaks. There's
little cause for claiming honor.
Therefore, within these spheres upon the
mountain, and in the dismal valley, you
were shown only those souls that unto
fame are known. Because the mind of one
who hears will not put doubt to rest,
put trust in you if given examples with
their roots unknown and hidden, or
arguments too dim, too unapparent.
>> Okay, great. Thank you. All right, so
what we're going to do now is we're
going to try try to put everything
together. Okay,
this morning we discussed the central
dilemma facing Dante. Okay, first of
all, he has to make sense of why his
life sucks, why he's in exile, why he's
begging people for charity. Um, at the
same time, he's trying to figure out why
the world sucks. Why is it that there's
so much chaos, there's so much
infighting, there's so much treachery,
there's so much hatred, there's so much
vengeance. And we talked about how um
previously there's hope that great
individuals such as Francis and Dominic
would change the character of the
Catholic Church uh so that it would
become less corrupt. But instead uh the
Catholic Church maintain to be corrupt
and change the radical nature change the
nature of the Franciscans and the
Dominicans. Okay. So what hope is there
in this world? Okay, that's central
question. [clears throat] In a world of
complete darkness, where is the light?
Okay. All right. So now we just read uh
the prophecy given to Dante saying,
"Yeah, your life is really really going
to suck after you leave heaven. You've
been to hell. You've been to purgatory.
Now you're in heaven. You've seen the
universe. And when you return, it's
going to be one of exile, one of
isolation,
one of poverty. And yet Dante is
has now purpose just like Inas, right?
Inas here hears that he will found a
great empire called Rome. And that
excites him, that propels him to
greatness, that propels him to victory.
And now Donna hears, "Oh yeah, when you
go home, you're just going to suffer all
the time." Yet it also propels him to
purpose and to greatness.
Why?
What is going on here? Why would the
idea of exile and isolation give him
hope?
>> Uh yes.
>> Um so difference between Dante and most
people who go through exile and
isolation is that he's given a preview.
He's given a peak behind the curtain.
When we say that it's easier for a rich
it's easier for a camel to pass through
the eye of the needle than it is for a
rich man to enter heaven, the rich man
will say to you, "Well, I can't see that
far." Or maybe they don't have the
willpower to keep themselves from being
wealthy and being evil. However, Dante
has had a glimpse of what lies behind
the veil and he knows that his life has
a purpose and is this guiding light,
this actual thing that keeps him going
onwards.
>> Um, okay. Yes. Let's be more specific
and concrete. Okay. Okay. Let's think
about this.
Dante,
let's imagine Dante
uh be if he didn't actually experience
hell, purgatory in heaven. Okay, his
father pairs him in his grandfather
pierced him in a dream. Okay, he's at
home. his grandfather perished to him
and Jim says that um my grandson in two
years time you'll be exiled from the
city you love the city you were born the
city that your family has inhabited for
generations
how would he feel despair right
but after he's been through this journey
the same vision the same faith gives him
hope and purpose. Why?
Uh yes.
>> Well, also as a poet, it's a great way
to focus your energy into creativity.
Well, like if you take off all the
distractions and you put all your energy
into creating, then he can think, okay,
maybe it's this time, this period of my
life where I can just put everything I
know and all my
everything I can accomplish.
>> Okay. Okay. So that's a good start.
Okay. Um if he is to achieve divine
harmony, he needs to go into isolation.
Okay. This isation going to last 20
years. By the way, it's going to take
about 20 years to to finish divine
comedy. Um okay. So that's the start.
Okay. He he appreciates that his purpose
is to go into exile and isolation in
order to write this divine comedy.
But this raises a question like well
that kind of sucks. I it's like going to
prison for 20 years and then my reward
will be I'm dead
right.
Um so I am reminded of something I once
saw on a Catholic website. So it was
actually about a saint a former non a
saint and her it was one of her quotes
and she said uh I I am impatient to
suffer and die for Christ. So there's
this let's say there's this almost
preoccupation with suffering and the
enobing of the spirit in Christ in
Catholic uh theology like they think
that suffering especially in the name of
Christ en nobles the spirit. So maybe
Dante is subconsciously uh
subconsciously likening himself to a
Christ figure and he thinks that
suffering for the sake of Christ for the
sake of his great work is a sign of
[clears throat] his faith and he would
be nowhere for this suffering than he
would have been if he did not suffer.
>> Yeah. Okay. And that's not wrong. And
that's exactly what Francis and Dominic
felt as well. Okay. But let's let's
think about this. Okay. You're Dante and
you're wring divine comedy not for
yourself, not for God, but for others to
read as well. So you want others to be
as inspired as you in serving God,
right? Do you understand? So he has to
somehow convince you to be like him.
Yeah. I mean like of course he
understands that the exile and the
isolation will allow him to write divine
comedy, but he needs you to move you,
inspire you in in in a way that allows
you to understand why he's doing what
he's doing and also to want to emulate
him, right? to want to also go in exile
in isolation in order to be truly
creative. So, how does he do that? All
right, let let's not let's just imagine
him just as a normal person just like
you and me, okay? He's no different.
And he is in the situation where he
knows he's going into exile in isolation
for the next 20 years
uh to write Divine Comedy.
And after he finishes, he's going to
die. That's what the prophecy says.
So, how does he
find hope and purpose in this fate?
uh
maybe it's kind of inspiration because
as a writer you must have a inspiration
which could allow you to have a great
work. So maybe I think [clears throat]
what Stanton want to do is not just try
to make money but he just try to create
a masterpiece uh in his own life. So
maybe that is yeah the reason why he
feel he got hope.
>> Okay. All right. So so let's think about
the sequence of events. Okay. This
prophecy doesn't happen in hell. It
doesn't happen in purgatory. It happens
in paradise. And it is the last prophecy
before he goes and fulfills his destiny
which is to meet God. Okay. So what does
he learn
in hell purgatory and paradise which
prepares him to accept this prophecy?
What is it?
these past two days, what have we
learned
about the universe? What are some ideas
that we've learned these past two days?
Let's let's just start naming them.
Okay. Uh yes.
>> Maybe it's because he witnessed the
light and the greatness and the beauty
of God with his own eyes and that gives
him the courage to continue.
>> Okay. Okay. Again, you're being too
general. I want I want specifics. What
did we discuss these past two days and
what impact would they have on Dante and
how they would change the way he sees
the world? Okay. Well, ask yourself this
question. These past two days, how have
reading Dante changed the way you've
seen yourself and the world? Think about
this question. Okay? Use your intuition.
Use your imagination. How have I changed
in the way that I see the world?
>> Yes.
>> Well, Well, you see the the human
himself as like the the middle of the
universe and then he is like
he's like what embodies the universe and
he's through through our actions we can
like improve the universe or person it
>> okay yeah exactly first the first thing
he's he he recognizes that you matter
your actions matter regardless of who
you are you do matter matter. Okay,
I mean she did something really really
good. I mean like she she she found
herself to God and then she broke this
vow and it matters. Okay, in her mind
it's like what? I mean like God's really
really busy, right? God's like taking
care of the universe and I'm just like
this little princess in this poor little
place and I break a vow but I hurt no
one and I was faithful to him all this
time but my one little action at this
one time does matter. It matters so much
that it changes
the universe. Okay, that's the first
thing that Donnie realizes I do matter.
Okay, so what I write does matter.
That's empowering, don't you think?
Right? Because like why else am I
spending 20 years writing a poem? And
the answer is because God is watching
you. Because everything you write will
be read by God and then it will be
reflected throughout the universe. With
my actions, I can change the very
trajectory of the universe. Okay, that's
the first thing that we learn. What else
did we learn?
>> Yes, I think it's also important to
remember that this is a two-sided coin.
Like uh on one hand, your actions matter
and you could change the universe. On
the other hand, your misactions matter
and your misactions could make the
universe worse. So instead of this
constant fear of damination or constant
fear of hellfire, Dante replaced it with
a a humanistic a humanistic fear of what
will my actions truly do? like he is
taking take he has taken the reigns back
from the devil and he's given the reigns
to himself.
>> Yes. Okay. This is really important
guys. Okay. At this time in history the
Catholic Church tells you to fear God.
You understand? Live a life of fear. Do
not do anything because you'll probably
screw it up. Right? And what we learn is
God is love. God will never judge you.
Only you judge yourself. Therefore, just
live the life you want to live. Live
your best life. Aspire to greatness. And
that's what God wants. Okay? God wants
will. He wants desire. He wants you to
be your creative best. So don't worry
about angering him. Don't be afraid of
him. Love him as much as he loves you.
Right?
Okay. Good. Really important, guys.
Okay. One, we do matter. Everything we
do does matter.
Number two is
God is non-judgmental.
He will never ever punish you for doing
what you think is right.
Okay? Just follow your heart. Good. What
else? What else have we learned these
past two days?
Just ask yourself what have you learned
these past few days? What ideas have
stuck in your head? Yes. Uh
[clears throat]
>> that the fear of unknown stops you from
um aspiring to the higher.
>> Yeah. Right. Good. Yeah. Don't be
afraid. Just love. Just trust. Okay.
Because love is the underlying principle
of the universe. God is all love. Okay?
Don't be afraid. Take the risk. Take
that leap of faith. Good. What else?
>> Like follow your heart and do the free
will and do not be restricted by the
material world.
>> Yes. Exactly. Okay. Don't care about the
judgment of others. If God's not going
to judge you, no one else is going to
judge you. Okay. Just follow your
intuition. Just follow your heart. Do
what you believe is right. What else?
Yes. You have to forgive yourself to be
a better person.
>> Okay. Yes. Okay. Let go of the past.
Forgive yourself. Good. What else?
>> You need to care about poor guy because
if you care about them, even give them
money, maybe you will go to heaven with
with him.
>> Uh no, that's not what my topic
believes.
>> Yeah.
Also the most important thing of course
is that there is intentionality in the
universe. We are all part of God's grand
design. Remember the metaphor that
Beatus uses is the body, right? God is
the mind. We're all part of the body. So
we are moving towards God's plan. Okay?
All right. So this is all that we've
learned these past few days. And think
about how if you learn if you believe
these things, you no longer fear exile.
You no longer fear isolation. Why?
>> Yes.
>> Well, because in your heart, you know
that you're doing the right thing. Like
if you like from your instincts and your
intuition, you didn't know if you did
the right thing, then obviously it
wouldn't make sense. But if you know
from just from your intuition that you
know the right thing, then it's probably
the right thing. You you like don't need
logic or something to like figure things
out. You just need to
>> So the most important thing and you say
this is like
knows it's not his fault for his exile
and isolation. This is really important
guys, right? It's not my fault. I didn't
do anything wrong.
Why is this? Yeah.
>> So this is something that uh confuses
me. Like uh earlier on you said that if
there's a will, there's a way. And you
use the like you use the example of
Picarda and Picarda
is in a similar situation to Dante. She
is oppressed by a militaristic force and
she is forced to go against her vows and
well how is Dante's situation different?
If he believed in will so much why
couldn't he have used the will to find
out a way to stay in Florence?
>> Okay. All right. So the so you raised
this question. Okay. And the um answer
is
their purpose is different. Do you
understand? The Carter's will is always
to serve God. To be married to God, to
live in the nunnery, right? What is
Tony's purpose?
What is his purpose?
>> Sure.
>> To write the divine comedy, guys. Okay?
Do you understand?
That's what his will is. His will is not
to be the mayor of Florence. His will is
not to be the pope. His will is not to
conquer his enemies. His will is to be
the poet. The greatest poet in human
history. That is what he wants. Okay.
Did you understand? Yes.
>> So like as we mentioned everything has a
consequence and then like Dante did end
up dying because of malaria after he
finished the divine comedy. Do you think
that is his consequence? like he had
fulfilled his will of writing this
poetry and then after that his mission
is complete and do you think that is
like his will or like God's will or like
>> okay so okay that's a great question
okay um why is it that he died after he
finished Divine Comedy and I'm going to
say something really strange for you
guys but let me ask you this question do
you think Dante was a healthy person
>> probably not
>> probably not guys okay
>> probably not here sick most of his life,
right? And that's probably probably why
he had the visions that he did because
he spent most of the time in bed
dreaming,
>> right?
>> Yeah.
>> So, I would argue that if it weren't for
Divine Comedy, he'd probably be dead at
40. He started Divine Comedy at maybe
around 40 and he died in his 50s. Do Do
you understand?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. I mean, like like it it was his
will that kept him going,
>> right? So you could say, well, it was
because he spent so much effort into
running the man that he exhausted his
body and he caught malaria and then he
died. But you can also argue, well, the
guy was probably not healthy to begin
with. Okay,
>> most most of these boys are not
athletes. They're not the healthiest
people you you you will meet.
>> They're often like, you know,
daydreaming or getting drunk or
something. Okay. But they're not working
out and stuff. Does that make sense?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Thank you.
>> Yes.
So something I'm curious about is
Dante's attitude towards
predetermination. Like if you look at
this passage. So he's basically
prophesying to himself like at the at
his time while he was writing this
passage all of these things that the
angel has said to a allegedly past
version of himself has already happened.
So he is trying to frame this as okay
I've been told that this is going to
happen. This is not a surprise to me at
all. Which just seems very uh
wishywashy.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. Let's let's be
clear. Okay, Dante is writing this not
to console himself, okay? But to give us
hope. Does that make sense? Okay.
Because we are Dante in the poem. So
when we read this, we shouldn't feel
despair for the fact that we're going
going ex into exile. It should give us
hope. We're trying to figure out why
this is the case. All right. Number one,
and this is the most important, is we
know it's not our fault, right? Okay.
And this is important because what's the
number one reason why divorce
traumatizes children? You guys know
they think it's their fault. Okay. And
that's why if they didn't think it was
their fault, it divorce wouldn't matter.
Okay? But children think this divorce
was my fault. And that's what
traumatizes them. Okay? So Dante
hears like, "Oh, it's not my fault. This
is all pre-ordained." and they they will
blame me but God himself knows that it's
not my fault so my heart can rest at
peace okay I can forgive myself uh I can
forgive others okay so so let's focus on
this guys okay number one is let's see
on this clearly number one is Dante
knows it's not his fault okay let's keep
on going what Now,
I know, but let's let's let's think
about the psychology, okay?
>> You know, it's not your fault. Now,
what?
>> I'm interested in how he just accepted
this fate.
>> Yeah.
>> Cuz uh if if it's it's his fault, he was
like, "Yeah, I'll I I I deserve this,
but it's not his fault." He's like, "Why
this kind of things uh this kind of
accident happened to me?" And um is he
going to feel like kind of unfair or
just
>> Okay. Right. Right. right right. Yeah.
Go on.
>> Yeah. Because his to to to follow on on
to the his fate is part of his destiny.
So he embraces his destiny. Um and it
would be what's next. Embracing his
destiny.
>> Yeah. He now appreciates this is just my
fate. And it was it's part of God's plan
and it's my purpose to write Divine
Comedy. I don't know why. I don't know
what impact it will, but given the fact
that my grandfather told me that I'm
going to go into exile and isolation,
it's not my fault. And I know for a fact
that God loves everyone, that God has a
plan. There's a reason, a perfect reason
for everything.
And I'm part of this plan, then I should
just do what God tells me to do, which
is red comedy,
right? And we call this what? Faith,
hope, love.
Okay? That's his salvation. The faith.
Faith is understanding the nature of the
universe that God loves us. God has a
plan and if we just follow the plan by
following our intuition, things will
turn out okay. Okay? We don't know how,
we don't know why, but they'll turn out
okay. That's what faith is. Hope is to
see what your what the future is. The
future is you'll finish divine comedy
and that's enough. Okay? And then love
is why are you doing this? You're doing
this for love of Beatric, love of
family, love of God. Okay? Right? at
these three things which he discovers
here. Get Yes.
>> So to sum it up yours you your idea is
that Dante believes in predetermination
by God, right?
>> Okay. All right. So let's think about
this. Okay.
This this is a good question. Okay. This
is actually a really good question. So
So thank you. Okay. We just said these
past two days that free will is
fundamental law of the universe.
We also say that if there's a prophecy
then there has to be predetermination.
So how can we make sense of this
paradox? Is this a paradox? Yes,
>> that arrow the the arrow thing that um
the go the go was mentioning right
because because if there's no ordinal
relationship between those things
predetermination is just determination.
There's no what's what comes first and
what comes next.
>> Okay. Yes. Well, I just I just say that
free will is like there's a there's like
a plan, but like we can choose through
we free will to either follow it or not
follow it. Like there there is
definitely a plan for every person, but
like you don't have to follow. There's
like people that go against their
intuition, right? Like they do.
>> That's right. Okay. So remember what
free will is. Okay. God loves you. God
is trying to pull you back to him
because there's an aspect of God inside
of you, right?
You desire to return to God. Okay, this
is the fundamental logic of the
universe. God loves you. God's calling
you back to him. You love God. You're
returning to God,
but you have the free will to deny God
and turn away from God. That is the free
will. Uh yes. So a followup question. So
if God has a plan and God God allows you
to use your free will to turn away the
plan, then let's look at the people who
prosecuted Dante who drove him out of
Florence. So are you because God knows
that these people are going to drive him
out from Florence. Therefore God must
have set the plans for these people and
therefore God God's plan for these
people his all good plan for these
people is for them to do such an evil
thing to drive him out of Florence. So
why
>> does anyone want to respond to this?
>> Those people sin on their own on behalf
of their own free will, right? It's not
God's plan for them to commit do what
they did.
>> In that case, how did God know about it?
>> Okay. Okay. You're assuming God cares
what happens here. God doesn't really
care what happens here, right? What
God's plan is is for us to return to
him. Does that make sense? God is
calling for us and we want to return to
him. So our actions here is to return to
him. Okay? And what happens here on this
planet doesn't really impact
um this grand logic. Does that make
sense?
Um, I don't I don't think you made it
clear like how how God knew that what
the bad guys were going to do if the bad
guys really had free will and if they
and if God God's plan for these bad
people is for them to be bad, how could
a good God do this thing?
>> Right? So in this prophecy, what happens
to all these people who
have persecuted Dante?
They have a worse faith than Dante. Do
you understand? Yes. Dante have exile in
isolation.
But these people have a much worse faith
than you do.
So what what's the problem here?
>> The problem is uh if God's plan is for
these people to be bad, then how could a
almighty good God like make people do
bad and then condemn them to hell? It's
like playing a puppet show. Why would
you make the bad puppet?
Well, I mean I mean if you do bad
things, bad things are going to happen
to you, right? If I hit you, you're
going to hit me back.
>> I think there uh shouldn't be the
dichotomy of bad and good in any serious
uh academic discussion. I mean uh we are
uh you know in a very complex world and
uh of course there is retribution
retribution there is you know uh good
and bad but we cannot really you know
just tag or anybody or any events just
with very simple uh you know uh tag of
good and bad which will make make
discussion very difficult. So I I think
the the minor characters uh in Danty's
life or in Danty's books uh um you know
are also part of the plan as Danty
intended but um uh but you cannot say
that their actions are evil uh and
therefore it should not be tolerated by
God. I don't think there is there is no
need there's any need to discuss even
this logic.
>> Okay. You Yes.
>> Yeah. I was thinking I think earlier we
were making a point where like people do
what they think is good based on their
judgment. So I was thinking what if
those people were doing what they
thought was like good was the right
thing and then they um sent like Dante
in exile but then it was like objectally
bad because like God didn't want it so
that's why they got punished. That was
kind of my interpretation. I don't
>> Okay, look the situation is never as
complicated as this. Sorry. The
situation never as simple as this.
Right. But what happened was that
um Donn was sent into exile and he said
you and they said to him, "You can come
back, but you must confess to certain
crimes and D's like no screw you. I
didn't do anything wrong."
>> Do you understand?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> So, it's not it's it's not simple. It's
not black and white.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> Do do you understand?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Never never in life are things
black and white.
>> Uh uh
there are four people here. Okay. So,
let's go one by one. Okay. Uh you first.
It's also that we're framing the people
who say exiled Dante, they were doing a
bad thing. But if they had been more
more pure in their thinking and their
intentions, maybe they wouldn't have
have gone against Dante. So they had
maybe God had a good predetermined plan
for them, but they went against it
because they didn't look at the the
situation in the right way.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. So So something I
want to say is this. Okay.
Um,
no one is really at fault because the
situation in Italy is one of complete
chaos and warfare. Okay? It's um, kill
or be killed. So, in their eyes, what
they're doing is they're trying to
protect the families. They're trying to
protect their children.
Okay? So this is a problem that D is
trying to deal with. We live in evil
time where everyone is forced to do evil
and so what can we do about it? Okay,
that's a question that D is facing. For
whatever reason, we just end up in a
situation where evil rules and those who
commit the most evil are usually the
ones who triumph in this world. Maybe
not in the next world, maybe they'll go
to hell, but in this world, they will
always triumph. And so, what can we do
about this? And the answer isn't, oh,
we'll just wait for God's judgment day.
Let's No. No. There has to be a
different answer. We're trying to figure
figure out what it is. Okay. Uh, yes.
>> Yeah. Something that came came to mind
on top of what we just discussed was
simplicity. When Dante embraced his
destiny to to write Divine Comedy, it
simplified his whole world being down
into It's simp something that comes to
mind is simplicity is close to God.
Whatever God is, whatever love is, it's
simple. I don't know if that makes
sense.
>> No, it makes perfect sense, right? He
now has focus. Before he had doubt, he
had ego, he had fear. Now he just has
focus. Like I'll just write the D comedy
and
uh I I'll I won't die until I finish it.
Okay. Now he has complete will. The
absolute will is now the contingent will
as well. Okay. So that's so so that's
what this prophecy has done for him.
It's given him the future and he knows
his place in the universe. Okay. Uh so
so did you have a comment or question?
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Well maybe the point
was that um Dante
he would have never gone through
everything if the people
um chose to do not chose to do evil to
him. So through the so like it's a bit
complicated but like
um they chose to do that but if they
didn't choose that then through free
will then Dante would have never went
through all of this. So like how like so
in the end it wasn't really a plan from
God himself.
>> Right. But what D recognizes recognize
that everything has a purpose.
Do you understand? Everything has a
purpose and that's why he's able to
forgive others because as long as he
achieves his purpose then everything
>> so so he still he still would have
achieved his purpose if he wasn't
persecuted.
>> No, he would not have been able to
because he would not have been in exile,
right? You need isolation. You need
exile in order to write Divine Comedy.
>> So he's so he needed other people to
persecute him basically.
>> Um but others We're going to persecute
him anyway because this is all political
faction fighting, right? This is all
political violence right now.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. All right. Did did you have a
question?
>> Yeah. Because you know uh first first of
all I think original thing is kind of
thing that been written in the Bible. It
means that every people have sin. This
is for sure and you can't say that it's
not my fault. You can say this is not my
thing. You know because saying is
original one. Everyone have to be blamed
because we we we steal the apple right
from the tree. And secondly, I think the
Odyssey is also kind of thing maybe that
influence maybe because in Odyssey uh
you know the hero just always have to
excel, right? So maybe Dant maybe Dings
are every hero need to be uh excelled
maybe.
>> Okay. All right guys. Okay. So let's
let's now focus on the question. Okay.
The question is, Dante is living in a
time of pure hopelessness
whenever you do
uh ends up causing even more problems.
And so for Dante,
what is the solution? What is the only
way forward? Okay. And this prophecy
tells him, you will go into exile and
isolation.
And in isolation, it doesn't say this,
but you're but it's to write Divine
Comedy. Okay. So, why would the divine
comedy
be a possible solution to all this chaos
and darkness and violence?
Why?
Uh yes,
>> because it reunites all the types of
thinking, the religion, and it guides
through love. And because love is
uniting, well, it it's way to just unite
everyone whatever the culture or area.
>> What does divine comedy do and bring to
the world that is missing in Europe at
this time?
It just like it proposes a solution for
people who like went through suffering
without understanding why they went
through suffering because like they went
through suffering before because of
obedience but through the Catholic
church but now he proposes a new
solution that you can go through
suffering because you actually want to
make a positive change in the world and
not just like obey the church.
>> Okay. But but how? Okay. So you suffer
and now you can now explain your
suffering. What do we call this?
Older.
No. Okay. So, so, so think about this.
Okay. This is really important. You
what? No. No. Think about this.
before divine harmony,
this was not this did not
um this was not present in Europe and
with because of its absence people were
committed tremendous violence against
each other. People were
uh just fighting all the time. Okay. So
Dante decides I must go into isolation
exile in order to write the vine comedy
in order to bring this into Europe.
Right?
What is the vine comedy
>> and why does it change the destiny of
your forever?
>> Is it about forgiveness?
How people as individuals can forget
forgive their themselves and each other?
What allows you to forgive someone? What
allows you to forgive someone?
>> To recognize a sin and to recognize it's
not necessarily their fault.
>> To recognize it's not their fault. And
how do you do that?
>> By unconditional love.
>> Observation.
>> Observation is not enough. What else do
you need? Let's let's talk concretely.
Okay. No, let's figure let's talk
concretely. Give me an instance. We we
we forgive someone. Okay. Just tell us a
story and we'll figure out what's going
on. Like if someone gets angry, he hits
you and then you just think it's because
of his emotions and it's okay. Like
>> but what allowed you to know it was his
emotions?
>> Like knowledge about
>> what what knowledge?
>> Empathy.
>> Empathy. Yes. Okay. What allows for
empathy?
>> Love.
>> Wisdom or like
>> Okay. When when you're saying when we're
saying this person hit me because he's
angry,
he's emotional, so he lost control. What
are you really doing?
>> Uh consideration. Considering the
person, you go beyond, you know, you go
above him in your
knowledge and reasoning.
>> What does it mean to go above your
reasoning and your knowledge?
>> You put yourself into his shoes or
>> How do you do that though? What?
Imagination.
>> The imagination guys. Okay. Do you
understand the imagination? Yes.
>> I think it's also like looking inside
yourself inside
like uh before like when D was first
exile he he was not thinking about all
of us. He was thinking about the
outside. He was thinking objectively
these guys harmed me and objectively I'm
so angry about it. But when he looks
inside that he can find the strength to
continue and the strength to forgive. So
he's uh using this to tell people to
look inside not outside.
Uh
>> yeah because empathy is basically u
imagining what would I do if I were him?
>> Exactly. Okay. Does that make sense to
you? Okay. When you forgive someone,
it's an act of imagination,
right? Because you're imagining that if
I were that person, I would also get
angry and hit someone.
>> Do you understand?
>> Sometimes it's also knowledge. Like in
some case, you can imagine the person
and then sometimes you just know why
he's angry,
>> right? And that now is a solution,
right? If we can increase the
imagination of everyone in Europe, this
violence,
this infighting, this chaos, this greed,
this corruption would have to
decrease. Not come to an end. You can't
do that. But it would have to at least
decrease. Does that make sense?
And before people lacked an imagination.
Why?
Why did people lack an imagination?
>> It's all about obedience to God. That's
the church. The Catholic Church
>> the obedience. But what emotion was
limiting your imagination? What emotion?
What emotion limits your imagination?
It's what?
>> Fear.
>> Fear. Right? You understand? So let's go
back to to your instance where someone
hits you, right?
If you're afraid, what do you do? You
hit him back. You understand? So it's
the fear that limits your imagination.
And at this time in Europe,
fear is dominant emotion. So if Dante is
to release people from their fear, he
must prove to everyone that God is love.
You understand? And once he does that,
the imagination now is released and
people can be imaginative and this will
mark a new age in Europe and basically
let Europe conquer the world.
My question now is how does Dante prove
to everyone that God is love?
Everyone now lives in a time when
they're afraid of God. when they think
that if I sin, God will punish me and
send me to hell for all eternity. The
fear is what limits imagination.
What allows Dante to prove to the world
that God is love. Don't be afraid of
God. Yes.
>> So basically, he's making the unknown
unknown. So like uh people are scared of
hell. They're scared of burning in
hellfire. And to be honest, they don't
really know that heaven exists here. And
Dante, Dante in the story here, he's
taking a role of a pilgrim and he's
going to all these places and he's like
a tour guide and he's saying, "Oh guys,
this is here. This is that this happens.
That happens. As long as you don't do
that, this won't happen to you." And
he's turning the unknown into a no. And
that's how you remove fear.
>> Okay. So, let's just say that Dante
opens university and says, "In this
university, I'm going to teach you to be
not afraid of God. And here are the
reasons why you should be afraid of
God." Okay. Would it work?
Probably not. Okay. Probably not because
we know that Thomas Acquaintus tried it.
It didn't work.
The Franciscans tried it. Didn't work.
The Dominicans tried it. Didn't work.
Okay. But Dante, he was able to prove
that God is love. How?
>> He has to live it.
>> Excuse me.
>> He has to live it and he has to write
the divine comedy to channel himself as
the example.
>> Okay. Yes. Okay. Okay. The divine comedy
is what proves it. Do you understand?
Because what is divine comedy? Yes. Go
ahead.
>> Well, um you know God loves you because
he gave you the free will. Like you like
I mean the divine comedy says that
through the will you can decide your own
fate or your own destinies.
>> But but that's just logic. That's just
reason. I'm I'm saying like like how do
you convince someone that God is love?
>> Right. And it has to with divine comedy.
>> Yeah.
>> All right.
So what's going on?
Why would Divine Comedy prove
that God is love?
And and we just said that if Dante were
to open a university and lecture on God
is love, it wouldn't work. No one would
care.
uh they need to let the readers or the
the audience go on the journey uh like
he did to embody and to empathize.
>> What is art guys? Tell me what what is
art? Why is art different from
everything else?
>> Yes.
>> Uh it's like the difference between a a
encyclopedia definition of the emotion
anger and a piece of art titled anger.
So like uh the encyclopedia
edition tells you, it doesn't show you.
It tells you what anger is. It's
quickening of the pulse, cortisol, etc.,
etc. But the art you look at the art and
you feel it for yourself. You can
interpret it for yourself even. But with
your intuition, you arrive at the same
general conclusion.
>> And art is a channel of consonance uh
between the creator and the
uh observer or the experiencer.
truth uh truth because divine comedy if
divine comedy contains the truth and
reflects the truth over time across
dimensions across different mediums
it'll persist and therefore it's proven
>> yes okay yes did you have a yeah uh art
is just like expression of like just
expression of of of um ideas that you
get from God you don't like philosophy
for example is just like logical ical
thinking and you can do that by yourself
but expression to express art you need a
higher form to be inspired by something.
>> Okay. Okay. All right. So, so let's be
very specific. Okay. Again, use your
intuition. Did did you have a comment or
>> um it's a very simple one. So, I feel
like it's just kind of similar to how
the divine comedy state is longest
because we could resonate with it so we
believe in it. So, that's why it's the
truth.
>> Okay. Okay. Yes. But but but I want to
be specific. Okay, I want each and every
one of you to think of a movie or a song
or a painting or novel that has changed
you. Can you think of something that has
changed you? A piece of art that has
changed you. Okay, just name it.
>> Yes.
>> Uh for example, like the you know the
the movie uh the ter Terminator because
you know the movie that
>> is not a piece of art by the way. Okay.
>> Inception. Uh Inception. Okay. Yeah.
Bruce Lee.
>> Boo Lee. The movies Bruce Lee. Okay.
His dark materials by Philip Pullman.
>> What? What? What? What?
>> His dark materials.
>> Is is that a novel?
>> Yeah.
>> By by what?
>> Uh, it's about growing up and it's about
>> Oh, so Coleman His Dark Materials.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. Yes. I I've
actually read that. So, so I I actually
know this exam. Okay. But tell us why
it's changed you as a person.
>> Why?
like like Philip Pullman reading reading
his start materials has given me a new
perspective what happens after I die. So
uh this is kind of personal but I used
to be a Christian. I used to have this
vague faith that if I was good I will go
to heaven and everyone who is bad
towards me will go to hell. And when I
read his dark materials it's like being
freed and being burdened all at once. So
sometimes the sometimes the emotions I
feel when I am hurt are no one's fault
but my own and any closure that I can
find I have to find within this world
because after we die all of us are equal
every soul is equal and we be become new
life so I need to have initiative I need
to forgive and I need to avenge myself
>> okay all right so that's great okay so
so this is an example of transformation
right your worldview your worldview has
changed The way you perceive yourself,
the way you perceive the world is
different. But what was it about
historic materials
that made this transformation possible?
>> Uh personally I would say it's the
story. It doesn't force a moral upon me.
I just read the story and I follow the
journey of the protagonist and I get
emphasized of them.
>> Okay. All right. All right. Okay. Yes.
Okay. Did you have a question or
comment?
Yeah, I think it it names something in
yourself that was that used to be
unnameable that you don't know how to um
explain it and someone did it for you
and and through it their music you you
you feel that um
emotions in your heart that like finally
now you you you had this realization
that that oh this really speaks to me
and now I know how to
>> resonance Yeah. All right. So, so, so
let's go back to his dark materials.
Okay. Let let me ask you this question.
Okay.
>> Do you did you cry when you read his
dark materials?
>> Yeah.
>> Did you laugh?
>> Yeah. Sometime.
>> Did you were you angry?
>> Yes. Extreme.
>> Okay. So, do you understand guys? First
and foremost, art is an intense
emotional experience.
You guys understand this?
If a song moved you, the movie touched
you, it's because it was an intense
emotional experience for you.
Okay, that's one. Two is this intensive
of emotions. What it does is it goes
into you or it opens you and allows for
the entry of the ideas into you. Okay?
And these ideas, these words, these
songs, these melodies, it's almost like
a virus that grows over time, right? So
the transformation doesn't happen like
today, but happens over time. And you
don't even know it's happening.
And then over time, what happens is that
your very perception of reality
changes.
Does that make sense?
That is why the divine comedy was proof
of God.
Okay? Because God could enter you and
God could transform the way you saw the
world.
That's what divine comedy is meant to
do. It's meant to fill you with love.
It's meant to fill you with God. It's
meant to give you hope, faith, and love.
Do you understand? It's a piece of art.
So what it does is what every piece of
art does. It shakes you emotionally. It
makes you afraid. It makes you happy. It
makes you angry. It makes you It
[clears throat] makes you emotional.
Okay? It's able to do so because it's
truth and beauty.
Does that make sense?
>> Yes.
>> All right.
And that's why divine comedy marks a
radical turning point in European
history. It doesn't happen right away,
right? It takes about 100 years, but
because it's so beautiful, because it's
so truthful, people are drawn to it.
They will read it. And when they read
it, they will transform because of it.
And as they are transformed because of
it, it will inspire them to create
tremendous pieces of art. The
Renaissance, those painters,
Michelangelo, Donatello,
they all read the line comedy. Okay,
this why and how do we know this?
Because the Renaissance occurred in what
city?
Florence. Is it all just a coincidence?
Right? Why Florence and why not Venice?
Why not Gene? Genua, right? Why Florence
specifically?
Does that make sense, guys?
>> Wouldn't Wouldn't they like ban the
Divine Comedy in Thrones because it's
from Dante and they accept him?
>> That's a really good point. Okay. So, if
you analyze this and you're like, "Wait
a minute here. It's heretical. It's
heresy. It's critical of the of Catholic
Church." They were not their banners.
Why not?
>> That you're wrong. No, they were not
there
is uh already uh got into a force of
itself. So it's any attempt to ban it
will just backfire.
Oh no, there's there's a very good
reason why they would not fear ban
comedy. Why not?
Now there's some history.
Where does art come from? If someone
like Leonardo appears and he's able to
take the Mona Lisa, what? How is he able
to do this?
>> He would go against God to me.
>> He would go against God because they're
like divinely inspired pieces of work.
>> Exactly. Do you understand this? Okay.
To try to burn down a painting to try to
destroy an artwork would be to go
against God.
that who dares go goes against God,
right? Because
at this time in history,
you see Leonardo paint the Mona Lisa,
right? You ask Mona Lisa, "Hey,
Leonardo, how were you able to do this?
He told you I didn't do this. God did
this, right?
There's no other explanation." He's
like, "Well, because of my synapses were
connected in a certain way."
No, it's like God. Sorry.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Again, I'm gonna nitpick your
logic here. So, you said that uh Dante's
Divine Comedy and the Renaissance occur
occurred to in the same city, Florence.
And you say that that's because of
Dante's or by extension of God's
influence. And I would have to say that
there are genuine historical reasons why
Florence is a fertile ground for the
Renaissance. There is the inflow of
trade caravans and there's its uh
fractured nature. A fractured state
actually contributes to a flourishing of
diverse ideas and there is a status as a
city instead of a suburb. So there's a
high concentration of intellectuals and
its traditional status as a seminary as
a place of education. So I think there's
loads of reasons and it's not
necessarily because of Dante.
>> I don't dispute this and if you talk to
any academic he'll explain to you these
very reasons. Okay, you have the
Meduchi, the begging family, who are the
patrons of the arts. You have the fact
that this is a city-state system, so
there's no central authority. The pope
cannot enforce his authority on
Florence. You had, as you point out, the
trade, the wealth. There are lots and
lots of really good reasons. Okay. But
my question is why Florence and not
Venice or Genanoa or any other of these
Italian city states, right? What did and
what did it happen after Dante not
before Dante in fact the Renaissance
happened I would say about 100 years
after the death of Dante okay and that's
enough time for the company to fully
fully incubate the culture does that
make sense because you need to create
mass right so maybe after Donnie died
there maybe like 50 manuscripts and then
maybe 100 manuscripts then a thousand
manuscripts okay but you need time for
this artwork to fully embed itself in
the imagination and in the culture.
Okay. [clears throat]
Okay. So, so again, we can argue forever
what was the cause of the renaissance.
Okay. But I'm just saying for this
class, the purpose of this class, just
take this leap of faith and trust me
when I say that it was Dante's Divine
Comedy that enabled the Renaissance.
Okay.
All right. Personally, I would say that
it was a huge factor renaissance, but I
would not say that it was it directly
enabled it. It was just a step in the
great river of history.
>> Okay. Well, what I would like to do is
teach Dante to the entire world and
we'll see which parts of the world
accept Dante. And I guarantee you the
parts of the world that accept Dante,
regardless of where they are, it could
be in China, it could be in the Middle
East, it could be in Africa, I don't
care which parts, but I guarantee you
this, whichever parts of the world, make
Dante part of the curriculum.
Make every child read Dante, I guarantee
you they will flourish
more than other parts of the world. I
make you this promise. Okay.
>> Uh yes,
>> that's super powerful.
>> We sh we shall see that. Yeah. And
that's my mission. Okay. This is why I'm
teaching Dante right now. It's part of a
larger mission to spread Dante around
the world. And I guarantee you those
parts of the world that do uh love Dante
will flourish. Wh what what what does
Florence mean by the way? Do you guys
know?
>> Fenzi spring, right? I
>> I thought I meant flourishing.
>> Yeah. Flourish. Spring. Flora. Same
thing,
>> right? Okay. And And was it Greek for
flourishing? Do you guys know?
What's it Greek for formonia?
Anyway, any anyway I went off topic
anyway. Okay, but like but you see
see how what what's happened, right? D
is facing dilemas. Okay, his life sucks.
All of York sucks. Okay, and then he has
this prophecy and he understands, okay,
now my mission is to write Divine
Comedy. Okay, that's why I'm going to
exile. That's why I'm going into
isolation.
Because by writing the divine comedy, I
can bring the imagination to the world.
And it's imagination that is our
salvation.
All right? So, the divine comedy must be
the greatest piece of art in the world
for this to happen. And if I were
writed, I don't have to fear the
Catholic Church because the Catholic
Church knows this must be the work of
God. All right? I can say whatever I I
don't care what I say. As long as it's
beautiful and truthful, it will
um be saved. Okay? And so what saves it
is the poetry, the beauty of the words,
right? And again, unfortunately, we
don't speak Italian. Uh but if you were
actually to read the divine comedy in
Italian, you cannot help but be
emotional, right? You cannot help but be
moved by the words.
And
um you will feel
I think
you I I I actually don't know this
because I never tried but I I I bet that
for some people they actually have an
out-of- body experience where they will
actually transcend the physical form and
be more in touch with the divine. It it
would be like taking Iawaska or a
psychedelic of some sort. Okay. All
right. if if you were to actually
practice um resetting the divine comedy.
Does that make sense? Yes.
>> Um I'm just uh you said that any any
country any any region that uh adopts
Dante as part of the core curriculum
would flourish and I would just like to
point out that the country that most
definitely does this right now is
probably uh in Italy and I don't know
what's your opinion on how they're doing
but I don't think Yeah.
>> Uh yes. Well, actually, I was in Italy
in Florence and or near Florence and
I've talked to people who studied the
Divine Comedy for six years and they
they all say that they hated it because
the teacher didn't like they like they
didn't do like teach it like you. It's
like totally different experience. They
they like only looked at the grammar and
at the language, but they didn't
actually like understand what you're
saying about the law of an imagination.
It's like really like plain in it.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Like they don't teach it the same way as
you teach it.
>> Look, look, look, look. You can make
anything terrible by making it by
testing it, right? Like you just add
test or anything. It's going to be
terrible because you're not because test
just force you to abandon your
imagination, right? And that's why I say
you want to read Divine Comedy, you have
to use your intuition, your imagination,
okay? And you just truly understand it.
then you will transcend. Does that make
sense?
All right. Okay. All right. So now let's
talk more about faith, love, and hope.
Okay. I I want to be very specific here
about what these things are. So we're
going to do is we're going to go to
candle 24 and I'll set the scene. Okay.
The scene is
Dante and Beatatrice are in heaven
and they and Beatric becomes Dante's
teacher and they are exploring the
cosmos to find more about how heaven
works to find out about the nature of
reality, the nature of God. So what do
you think happens now? Can you guys
guess?
Do you guys know what happens now?
We just talked about this. You
learned
and you finish your learning and now
what?
>> Test.
>> There's going to be a test, guys. Okay.
>> There's going to be a test.
Um, yes. So, before Dante can meet God,
um, he has to prove he's worthy. And to
do that, you have to pass an examination
or or an oral examination. So there's
going to be three apostles
um
Peter, John, and James. And each of
these apostles is going to test Dante on
a concept.
Um the first concept is faith, what is
faith? Second concept is what is hope?
Third concept is what is love? And only
if
Dante
answers all three to the satisaction
uh of these apostles, can now he ascend
to the highest realm, the imperium? Does
that make sense? Okay, so this is really
funny. You're in heaven and uh they make
you take take an examination.
Okay, so you can never ever escape
tests.
All right. So, this is the qu the test
of faith. And by the way, what's
happening is that Beatrice has taught
Dante and now Beatrice has to observe
Dante. Okay? She cannot participate. She
cannot help Dante. Dante is now by
himself. Okay? He now has to prove that
he's absorbed the true teachings of
heaven. All right. Okay. So, kind of
count 24.
>> Candle 24.
Oh fellowship that has been chosen for
the blessed lamb's great supper where he
feeds you so as always to fulfill your
need. Since by the grace of God this man
receives foretaste of something fallen
from your table before death has
assigned his time its limit. Direct your
mind to his immense desire. Quench him
somewhat. You who forever drink from
that source which has sought and longing
seek. So, Beatus and these delighted
souls formed companies of spheres around
fixed poles, flaming as they revolved as
comets glow. And just as in a clock's
machinery to one who watches them, the
wheels turn so that while the first
wheel seems to rest, the last wheel
flies, so did those circling dancers, as
they danced to different measures, swift
and slow, make me jud a judge of what
their riches were.
>> Okay, stop. Okay. All right. So guys,
um, for homework, not only do I want you
to reread what we discussed today, but I
also want you to look at artwork,
imagery inspired by the vine comedy,
okay? It's a very visual poem. And
there's lots of paintings, lots of
artwork inspired by it. So that you know
how creative it is, but you but you also
recognize how crazy all this is. Okay.
>> Verse 19. From that sphere which I noted
as most precious, I saw a flame come
forth with so much gladness that none it
left behind had greater brightness. And
that flame whirled three times brown
beatrus while singing so divine a song
that my imagination cannot shape it for
me. My pen leaps over it. I do not
write. are fantasy and all the more so
speech are far too gross for painting
folds so deep.
Oh you who pray to us with such
devotion, my holy sister, with your warm
affection, you have released me from
that lovely sphere. So after he had
stopped his motion, did the blessed
flame breathe forth unto my lady, and
what he said I have reported here. She
answered, "Oh eternal light of that
great man to whom our Lord bequeathed,
the keys of this astonishing gladness,
the keys he bore to earth. Do test this
man concerning the faith by which you
walked upon the sea. Ask him points
light and grave just as you please, that
he loves well and hopes well, and his
faith is not concealed from you. You see
that place where everything that happens
is displayed.
But since this realm has gained its
citizens through the true faith, it
rightly falls to him to speak of faith
that he may glorify it.
Just as the bachelor candidate must arm
himself and does not speak until the
master submits the question for
discussion, not for settlement, so while
she spoke, I armed myself with all my
arguments, preparing for such a
questioner and such professing. On
hearing that light breathe, good
Christians speak. Show yourself clearly
what is faith. I raised my brow, then
turned to Beatatric, whose glance
immediately signal to me to let to let
the waters of my inner source pour
forth. Then I so may the grace that
grants to me to make confession to the
chief sh centurion permit my thoughts to
find their fit expression and followed.
Father, as this truthful pen of your
dear brother wrote, that brother who
with you set Rome upon the righteous
road, faith is the substance of the
things we hope for and is the evidence
of things not seen. And this I take to
be its quiddity.
>> Okay. Stop. Okay. All right. So what's
happening is that uh Peter the apostle
is now uh testing Dante and the first
question is what is faith and what Donn
is going to do is he's going to repeat
what Paul
wrote in Hebrews. Okay, which is faith.
What does he say? Faith. Faith. Yeah.
Faith is a substance of the things we
hope for and and is evidence of things
not seen. Okay. All right. So, um this
entire situation is is kind of weird.
Why is it weird or paradoxical?
Peter asks Dante, "What is faith?" And
Dante's response is, "Well, I'm going to
refer to the expert on faith, which is
Paul. And I'm going to repeat what Paul
said, which is that faith is the
evidence of things unseen. Why is that
weird? Why is this entire situation
weird? I guess
>> well because she despises the Catholic
Church and Paul is the Catholic Church.
So why would he like recite his words
and not like the words of Jesus or
something?
>> Um so I think despise is a hard is is is
harsh. Okay. Yeah. He he he's critical
of the Catholic Church,
>> right? Okay. He thinks the Catholic
Church should be reformed, but you know,
he doesn't believe the Catholic Church
should be abolished. But but something
weird going on. Yes.
>> The weird thing going on is that all
this while Dante is talking about
imagination, intuition, and importance
of looking into himself. And he
criticized the traditional mode of
theological learning, which is to recite
things and then spew it back out in your
when it when it comes to your own
interest. And what he's doing right here
is that he's reciting something and he's
spilling it out. So what is he doing
here?
>> Yeah. So, so it is a bit weird, don't
you think? Right. So, Don is saying, you
know, use your imagination, use your
will, and now he's partaking in an
examination, right? Uh Hebrews, are you
looking for Hebrews? Uh Hebrews 11. Yes,
Hebrews 11 is is is where this is um is.
Okay. So, may maybe we'll just read a
bit of that. Okay.
Okay. So, this is written by Paul. Um,
and he's trying to explain what faith
is.
>> Um, Hebrews 11, uh, NIV. Now, faith is
confidence in what we hope for and an
and assurance about what we do not see.
>> Um, yeah. Right. But, but it goes on,
right? So, so, so, so, yeah. So, so, so
maybe you can have the whole passage.
Okay. Okay. So, there's something really
weird going on because where are they?
They're in heaven, right? So, basically,
who can you have questioning D about
faith?
Yeah. Well, no, not not but
how about Paul? Because Paul's the
expert on faith, right? If you're in
heaven, you can access anyone. Get Paul
to ask D about about faith.
So, clearly, this is a paradox, right?
And this is another way that Dante
um is signaling that he differs from the
official teachings. Okay? So yes, he's
going to repeat the official doctrine
which is that faith is the evidence of
things unseen, but he's going to make
subtle changes to it. Does it make
sense, guys? Because otherwise, why not
have Paul test you?
All right. Uh c can you just uh read
Hebrews 11? Okay.
Now faith is confidence in what we hope
for and assurance about what we do not
see. This is what the ancients were
commended for. By faith we understand
that the universe was formed at God's
command so that what is seen was not
made out of what was visible. By faith,
Abel brought God a better offering than
Cain did. By faith he was commended as
righteous when God spoke well of his
offerings. And by faith Abel still
speaks even though he is dead. By faith
Enoch was taken from this life so that
he did not experience death. He could
not be found because God had taken him
away. For before he was taken, he was
commended as one who pleased God. And
without faith, it is impossible to
please God because anyone who comes to
him must believe that he exists and that
he rewards those who earnest earnestly
seek him.
>> Okay. Stop. Okay. All right. Okay. So
you guys understand what's going on.
Okay. So faith is the idea
uh that you understand the nature of
reality that it's all designed by God.
Everything that happens is for a purpose
and everything is leading to this point
in history. That is what faith is. Faith
is the understanding of God. And here
again this is really important. Dante
would agree with Paul's understanding of
faith and that's why he repeats Paul's
uh understanding. Okay. But at the same
time, we need to be aware that Paul is
not present. This is like really really
weird, right? Paul's not present here.
He's not mentioned here. So, we have to
be suspicious about what's going on.
Okay? It seems as though Donn is just
reciting, but Donnie is going to make
some nuance changes to this
understanding. Okay. Can you can you
read please?
>> Verse 64.
And is the evidence of things not seen.
And this I take to be its quiddity. And
then I heard you understand precisely if
it is fully clear to you why he has
first placed faith among the substances
and then defines it as an evidence. I
next the deep things that on me bestow
their image here are hid from sight
below so that their being lies in faith
alone and on that faith the highest hope
is founded and thus it is that faith is
called a substance and it is from this
faith that we must reason deducing what
we can from psyogisms without our being
able to see more thus faith is also
called an evidence.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. So again, he
repeats Paul and now he's going to make
adjustments to Paul, right? So faith for
Paul is the evidence of things unseen.
It is the divine plan. It is what keeps
the world together. It is what moves
history. That is what faith is. What
does Dante say and how does it change
Paul? This is a really hard question,
but let's try to figure this out.
Okay. So Paul says that faith is
understanding
obeying the underlying
plan of the universe. Okay? That's what
faith is. There is a plan. There is a
God. Miracles do happen. You don't see
these things, but they do happen. That's
what faith is. You just tr you don't
trust your eyes. You trust your heart.
And then Dante says that faith is what
binds everything together. It is what
underlies everything. How is this
different? How how's this logically
different?
Can you repeat what he said? The next
deep things.
Verse 70. The deep things that on me
bestow their image here are hid from
sight below so that their being lies in
faith alone. And on that faith the
highest hope is founded. And thus it is
that faith is called a substance. And it
is from this faith that we must reason
deducing what we can from psyogisms
without our being able to see more. Thus
faith is also called an evidence.
>> Okay. This is really hard. Okay. Um, and
I'm actually may get this wrong, okay?
But I but but I think there's a
difference between what Paul says and
what Donnie says. Paul says that faith
is the belief in a grand plan. That
faith is what moves the universe.
But Donnie says something different.
What is this? Yes. He's saying that
faith are the cornerstones of the
universe but that you have to build on
these cornerstones by reasoning and
syogism.
>> So where does faith come from?
>> So he is saying that let me use an
example here. So let's say that you
don't follow Dante's advice and you use
logic to define everything. So you go to
logic your way out of believing that God
exists. However, what Dante is saying
here is that you just have to take it as
a matter of faith that God exists and
then you can build on the fact that God
exists and then figure out what you want
to what you want to know.
>> Okay. Okay. Okay. All right. All right.
So, so, okay. I'm going to tell you what
I think this is saying and I could be
wrong. Okay. And we I'll I'll just say
what I'm saying and we'll see if it
matches with the tax. Okay.
I think in Paul's formulation, what he's
saying is that the plan already exists
and you just have to believe it exists.
Okay? It's sort of passive. Does it make
sense? What Donnie is saying is that
faith is the underlying substance of the
universe
and it's what moves the universe and
it's from faith we can build things. But
this raises a question like where did
faith come from in the first place and
what he's trying to suggest. Okay, I I
may have this wrong. What they trying to
suggest is that it's an active thing
where we are projecting our faith is
what it faith our faith is what drives
the universe. Okay? In other words, it
is what faith is is our imagination and
it's the imagination that's the
animating force of the universe. So
we've gone from Paul which is this
passive just accept faith accept
miracles happen accept God h there's God
to one that's active like you we are
projecting our faith on the universe
which creates a universe which moves
things you understand okay so without us
there would be no faith without us there
would be no universe
that that I think is the difference okay
so can we just read it again make sure
that my interpretation is correct I
could be wrong okay but but let's read
it again and See if this is correct. All
right.
>> Verse 70. The deep things that on me
bestow their image here are hid from
sight below so that their being lies in
faith alone. And on that faith the
highest hope is founded. And thus it is
that faith is called a substance. And it
is from this faith that we must reason
deducing what we can from soloisms
without our being able to see more. Thus
faith is also called an evidence.
>> Okay. What do you guys think?
Do you think that this matches the text?
>> Yes. I have a question. Yes. What what
are the deep things that on me bestow
the image here?
>> Uh where is it
>> in the first line? that the things that
on me bestow their image here are hid
from sight below so that the being lies
in faith alone. So I mean he's talking
about things like angels and demons and
and God itself right the deep things the
things underlying reality the things
below reality
>> forces
>> to me
>> forces like underlying forces
>> things you can't see right spirits
right so these spirits must exist
through something and he's saying it
must exist through faith alone right but
then what's faith then and how how these
spirits come into being it must be an
active force. The imagination,
right? And the imagination can only come
from us or from God.
And I'm I I don't I'm just interpret say
it's coming from us, I think. Okay.
Um, this reminds me of an analogy I
heard about God being a clock maker and
whether the clock maker
um kind of designs the inards of a clock
and leaves it be and the clock runs
itself or um is there human agency in
the clock running? And I think um what I
hear is that Paul sounded more passive
in that um and and could be what was
mentioned as more predetermined that
things were set in motion. But here
Dante is you're you matter. You're an
active agent. Um imagine and do and
you're part of um the grand truth and
beauty of the universe.
>> Yes. Yes. And also like reason must be
based on the imagination, right? You
must believe God exists. You must
believe there is a plan to the universe.
And from that you can reason things out.
Okay? Reason and imagination are not in
conflict with each other. Reason and
imagination uh reason is built on top of
imagination. Okay? So again, we can
argue back and forth. And I I wish we
actually had a Donic scholar in here uh
who actually knows this stuff. Okay? But
I'm just I'm just guessing. Okay. This
this what my intuition is saying he's
saying. Okay. Do do you have foot notes
on this?
[clears throat]
>> Let's let
>> I look forward to rereading and I mean
this is I mean this is part of okay
what's very important about this text.
>> Okay. So so so so we'll figure this out.
Okay. So uh well go and do some research
guys. Okay. Tell me what this is
actually saying. I think this is a um
you he is suddenly changing the meaning
of Paul.
Okay, Paul again is passive. He's
active. What he's saying is that what D
is saying that's very important is that
faith is imagination. When you believe
in God, you also have to believe in
yourself. You also have to imagine.
Okay. Faith is an active
uh act of imagine of imagining. Does
that make sense?
All right. Okay. Okay, let's let's let's
keep on going.
>> Yes.
>> Oh yeah. So So what do you mean faith?
It's kind of thing you have to determine
your mind to to believe it so it will
exist or
if you don't believe it and the faith
just do not exist.
>> Okay. Okay. So so so let's let's clarify
this. Okay. In science, right? God
doesn't exist. If you can't see it, it
doesn't exist. Is is that correct?
Right. And what D is saying is that if
you do it that way, you'll never get
anywhere. All right. And yes.
>> Well, but no, but energy is something
that you talk about in size and energy
you can't see. So energy can be God
inside.
>> Sorry. Sorry. It's not something you
can't see. Something you can't measure.
>> Okay.
>> You can measure energy.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. Okay.
>> So if you can't actually measure it, it
doesn't exist. But then the but then
it's like you have all these holes in
science which is like what is
consciousness right no one is allowed to
ask this question what is consciousness
yes
>> so I'm actually really interested in
this question so like uh Dante has has
been shown like these deep things right
he has been shown these angels and
Beatus is leading him around like this I
mean I mean the Dante in the story not
Dante the author and D. So is the Dante
in the story's faith therefore
diminished because he has seen and has
proof of these things because he's no
longer believe in him on marital faith
anymore.
>> Um okay that's a really interesting
question and I think the simple answer
but but but does anyone have a response
to this?
The divine comedy is a product of his
faith.
Do do you understand? It's only by
having faith could he write the divine
comedy. No, no, no. I'm talking about
the Dante in the story, not the Dante
the offer.
>> Oh. Um,
okay. Yeah. Go ahead.
>> Yeah. Um, I'm just really looking
forward to understanding what love in
this case in Dante's mind is because it
it looks like faith faith looks like
love, sounds like love. So,
>> yeah. So
>> I think uh you know uh I uh I try to uh
read this uh text from on different
layers. So the fundamental layer for me
is textualist layer. So I'm trying to
read everything Italian and in the in
the uh you know in the presentation of
the concept of face I think I if I'm
totally I'm not fluent in Italian but I
think the word used for evidence
actually is agumente.
So it's not evident it's not it's not
evidence. So there I think there is a
major uh diversion between the English
and the Italian uh text. So if we take
the take evidence away and uh change it
to argument. So there is
>> it's not it's on it's it's on line 76
credensa. So English is not an exact
line is is face. I'm talking about
evidence.
Evidence. Evidence. Evidence in Italian
is evidence and in uh in the Dante text
it is argument. It never use evidence.
So it is argument. So wait sorry. Okay.
So so okay. Um let's think about what
does line actually means? Faith is the
evidence of things unseen. What what
does that line actually mean?
Faith is the evidence of things unseen.
What does this actually mean?
>> That it tells you your senses don't
don't like you you cannot trust your
senses cuz your senses didn't uh doesn't
catch catch it. But
>> wait right there's no evidence this
exists. Do you understand? It's all
faith. Faith is the only evidence. Faith
is the only argument.
>> I think the the the original word
argument is the perfect word because it
is just an argument. It is just a you
know a perception. It doesn't you do you
don't have to deduct anything from it.
That's faith
>> right. Okay. Yes. Okay. So that's the
idea. Okay. There is no evidence. Okay.
Beyond faith. You you have to believe it
exists otherwise it doesn't exist.
That's it. There's no point in arguing
about this because there's absolutely no
evidence otherwise.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I know. So back to my
question about the fictional Dante. Is
the fictional Dante's uh faith
diminished because he has proof of what
he used to believe in?
>> Okay, so um this is how I would
understand. Okay,
Dante the pilgrim would not have been
allowed to go on this journey
unless he had faith. Does that make
sense? Okay.
But within the faith, which is his
heart, there has to be some experiences
that confuse him, that blind him from
his true faith, which is like, why am I
in exile, in isolation, and poor? If I'm
truly worthy of God, why did God
um have this faith for me? Okay, so he's
going on this journey because he has
faith. And this journey is meant to
remove all the doubts and the fears
from him. Does that make sense? The
faith is always there. He wouldn't be on
this journey unless he had that faith,
right? And this entire journey is meant
to clarify for him why he has faith.
So you're saying that he goes on this
journey and he experiences all these
things of his own free will that it is
not poured into his brain. Uh
uh
okay.
So first of all, divine comedy, it's a
pure act of imagination, right? He
didn't actually go to heaven. Uh he
might have he he might have had visions,
but he didn't actually go to heaven. Um
and this pilgrim, it's meant for
it's meant to allow us to go on our own
journey.
Do you understand? And because he's
meant to represent us, then it depends
on who you are doesn't make sense. There
is no objective experience. It's all a
subjective thing where if you read the
text, you're going to have a different
experience as Dante than if I were to
read the text as Dante. All right. So,
this is a question that you have to
answer by yourself,
right? Okay.
Yeah. Yeah. So like I'm just curious at
where the line is. So we basically
established that uh faith is believing
in something despite material evidence
to the contrary or a lack of material
evidence.
>> That's I thought that's what we said.
>> Okay. So that what is that what you what
you saying?
>> Yeah. Okay. So so so Paul says faith is
the evidence of things unseen. Okay. So
um to put this in very simple terms.
Okay. There are things that exist in
this world that you can never prove that
to exist. If you try to do so by
science, by measuring it, you get
nowhere. Okay? You'll never prove God
exists. You will never prove conscious
exists. But if you are to truly
experience the world, if you're trying
to make sense of the world, then you
have to assume certain things about the
world through your faith. For example,
God exists, conscious exists, we are
connected to God. Okay? And from then
you can reason things out that help you
seek the truth. But there is no evidence
that these things that God exists was
was true in the first place. Okay? And
and that's why science today has run
into a dead end. Like I'm not sure if
you guys study science, okay? But you
look at physics, you look at
neuroscience, it's all a dead end.
Okay. All right. Then tell me in the
past 70 years what's physical what
breakthrough in physics have we had?
>> Um we have had the particle accelerator
which
>> technology I'm talking about physics
>> it has allowed us to uh have insight
into the particular things that make up
atoms.
>> What you are citing basically just
articles news articles. Uh you are not a
scientist. You cannot make that uh you
know even that comment uh you know what
what scientific findings uh
breakthroughs what are not you you
cannot make that judgment.
>> Look look look look you talk to any
physicist and he'll tell you the last
major breakthrough was quantum quantum
mechanics quantum physics. Okay after
that we we've had things like string
theory that's like okay but it's not a
major breakthrough.
>> Maybe maybe we should talk to a physic
physicist. Okay, then go then guys go go
home do do the homework. Okay, tell me
in the past 70 years what major theory
in physics have we had.
>> No, professor you're making an
extraordinary claim. So it the burden of
proof is upon you.
>> No no no I'm I'm telling you what I've
read like online. I I I'm telling you
what what my own research
>> your own
>> well I was a physicist I was physicist
from from the age not eight and I've
studied also physics uh you know uh you
know until college uh my intuitive
understanding is I agree with professor
Jang that uh the so-called breakthroughs
are just in the last 70 years or 50
years is just you know just basically
just speculation so I uh but I cannot
say that I really on the same level as
the top scientist in the world. Of
course, I I just, you know, amateur, but
I think uh uh you have to uh you have to
do your homework before you make any
comment. Thank you.
>> And just
>> Yeah. And just look at just look at
neuroscience like the the people living
>> uh can you hear me? Yeah. like like
people um dating back to maybe 5,000
years ago or maybe even before that
people who live in Amazon forest they've
been they since then they already been
started using um psychedelics like
Iawaska um but now we still have yet to
figure out how um it works. I mean we
know the theories like the synapses the
receptors but how they um they form all
those kind of how they have all those
experiences we don't know we we we've
been having that medicine for thousands
of years
>> okay and also like we don't even know
how they came up with iaska right
because iawaska is a blending of two
plants there's like a million plants you
could blend together right how do they
know that these two particular plants
together in a certain quantity would
induce the psychedelic experience.
That's pretty amazing to think about,
right? If it's just random,
uh, it would take a million years to
figure this out. How did they do that?
How are they able to figure out I will
ask
>> without one another the the the only um
the actually the psychoactive herb that
can only last for like 10 minutes 20
minutes but with the other herb among
millions of herb um they combine they
they they um create this Iawaska that
can actually give you a full experience
rather than just 10 minutes of tripping.
Yeah.
>> So there's no way it could have been
random, right? There's no way it could
have been random. It was not like okay
you know what what is try million plants
and see which which which two work out
right they could have been random
>> we've heard about the story of
right the the how you even translate
that the the guy who tried
>> herbs
>> yeah yeah who who taste this guy in
ancient China who taste like thousand of
herbs and um even got praised a few
times and and he wrote a book about all
all those herbs. I mean that that could
be not true but I mean
>> okay look look look look okay I was I'm
telling you no one knows how they came
up with this okay it it is the most one
of the most powerful psyched in the
world uh and it's safe and it gives you
this transcendental experience and as
you point out it requires two plants it
requires two herbs in a certain quantity
together okay and like it's like how do
they figure this out because there like
these millions of these herbs in the
Amazon, right? Yeah.
>> I'm saying that I absolutely agree with
what you say in the context of Dante.
So, back to your m stated mission for
this class is to spread Dante and make
people realize how good Dante is. And
I'm saying that uh I agree with your
mission. I think it's really great. But
if you try to make this super science,
if you try to elevate this above
science, above common knowledge, then I
think it'll be really hard to convince
people. you will not be able to achieve
your mission.
>> Okay. Okay. I didn't say D was better
than science. I said that if you just
work with the current um paradigms of
science, you get into a lot of dead ends
including consciousness, including the a
lot of things. Okay. All right.
Uh any other comments or questions? Yes.
>> Uh I I do I do believe what the
professor said because Dante is kind of
a solution. is kind of a possible way
for us to lead into new future. So it
doesn't mean that Danting just try to
deny ever you know philosophy or it can
be D is not on top of it but as Danting
is kind of a new channel I think maybe
this is new possible. Yeah. So,
>> do you guys remember in Kennel 2
Dante and Beatatrice were talking about
the um the dark spots on the moon and
Peter said to Dante, "You should do a
science experiment, right? Dante is not
anti-science.
He's not. In fact, he loves science. He
himself was a scientist.
Okay? So, this is not an anti-science
thing. But um but what Donnie is saying
is that you have to believe certain
things about the world if you are truly
to seek the truth. And certainly certain
these things are you know um are just
things you can't see. You can't you
can't ever know. You just have to
believe in them. That's that's what
faith is. Okay.
>> Um I want to share something. Um I
really appreciated David pointing out
the word argument whether it's evidence
or argument in in English. Um because um
what the verse that captured me was on
that faith the highest hope is founded.
So um to me this passage is about um
faith not just as um almost like a blind
faith that if you think about what Paul
could be saying um faith is just okay um
you don't see it but that's what it is.
So have faith in that. But this here is
where hope is founded. So it's a driving
force upon which imagination
um things people have action um it's a
driving force.
>> Exactly. Okay. So so um we we'll end
with this. Okay. What's the highest
hope? What is our highest hope?
Exactly. Right.
What what is the
what's the highest hope?
You can try to answer.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> I'd be curious to hear your answers.
>> But what is salvation then?
>> Yo, what is heaven? Return to God,
right?
Like like like we've been talking about
this like this like this morning which
is like God is calling to us and we are
calling to God. Okay. That's what that's
what the highest hope is to be able to
return to God which is our salvation and
redemption. Okay. Yes,
>> my highest hope is to make every every
organism, every living being in this
universe happy and safe and loved. And I
don't think that has anything to do with
returning to this God.
>> But that but that that's what
theologians say is returning to God.
Returning to God is if you return to God
by yourself, that's not enough.
Everything has to return to God. God has
to be made whole, right?
is God splitting himself up into the
world and now everything has to return
to God for the for the world to be whole
again. Okay. And that will be the
highest happiness, the highest hope.
>> And my point is we can't just look
inwards and be like I'll meditate all
day and this will be good. We have to do
works, do good works.
>> No one is saying meditate all day. D is
saying you have to like learn, you have
to debate, you have to inquire, you have
to experiment, right? That's what Don is
saying here. My question is has Dante
done any good works like Dante the
fictional pilgrim has he done any good
works as the result of his experiences?
>> I don't understand the question.
>> What what I'm saying is after he got
enlightenment so uh he realized that his
highest mission is to return to God and
to make God whole, right? By making
everyone around him return to God. So
what has he done towards this goal? I'm
talking about Dante the fictional
character, not the author.
Well, well, well, we we don't know
because we haven't finished the line
comedy yet,
>> right?
>> Okay.
>> Okay. When we get there, we'll we'll
know. We'll know what what he did.
>> Okay. Uh yes.
>> Clarification on faith. Um can I
interpret it as just fully committing to
a hypothesis? Like in Dante Dante's
terms, fully committing to the
hypothesis that fully committing to the
hypothesis.
>> Well, if you change the hypothesis of
faith, yes. Committing to your faith.
committing to your hypothesis that God
exists.
>> No, because hypothesis can be proven
wrong.
>> Oh, that's true. That's true.
>> The faith is a is the assumption the the
the thing from which everything must
come, right? In order to achieve the
highest hope, you need to have faith,
right?
Yes. I I think that the true value of
this class uh is not only is about
denting but also about God because
people right now they don't believe in
God. Most of them believe in money, the
power, the science, the AI. So which
means that we lost our faith, we lost
our hope, we lost our love. But if the
denting really, you know, can really
recall people's memory, maybe people can
can just on the one hand develop their
science for no problem. But on the other
hand, they should know the faith, hope,
and love is the most important thing
that can leave people to live together
happily and not just hatred or just have
war maybe. So I get asked a lot what I
think the path forward is. Okay, we live
in a world of war. We live in a world
where Donald Trump is president, you
know, and so what is the path forward?
And the answer is if we all read Dante,
our imagination would be activated and
we would um have the faith to achieve
the highest hope. Okay. The answer is
not in me. The answer is in you. The
answer is
by reading Dante to achieve your true
potential, your true self.
Okay. All right. So, so we we'll leave
that uh for now. We'll continue this
tomorrow. Okay. All right. So, but but
uh thank you. Um you're all improving.
It seems you're all transcending or
you're all being enlightened. Okay. And
that's really the power of Dante. Just a
few days of Dante is going to make you a
better person. Okay. So again, the
homework is to to reread what we read
and make sure you understand what's
going on. Okay? And again, all this is
my interpretation. Look for other
interpretations. They're all available
online, right? Um and really come to
your own understanding. And if you feel
that my interpretation is a bit off or
there's problems with um some of my um
arguments,
challenge us, okay? This is a place
meant for free debate, open dialogue. I
don't censor anyone. I don't stop anyone
from talking. Okay? All right, guys. See
you tomorrow.